<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A continuation of The dialogue between a Christian and a Quaker wherein the truth of those things objected against them in the first part, are fully confirm'd : together with a further account of their perilous and pernitious errors concerning the person of Christ, His satisfaction, justification, sanctification, the ministry, and immediate motions are in this second part, cleerly and plainly represented out of the writings of some of their principal, and most approved leaders / published for the common information of such as either really are, or may be, in danger of being insnared and intangled by them by Thomas Hicks.</title>
            <author>Hicks, Thomas, 17th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1673</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 178 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 51 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43724</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1919</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21822</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12171575</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12171575</idno>
            <idno type="VID">55411</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43724)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 55411)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 603:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A continuation of The dialogue between a Christian and a Quaker wherein the truth of those things objected against them in the first part, are fully confirm'd : together with a further account of their perilous and pernitious errors concerning the person of Christ, His satisfaction, justification, sanctification, the ministry, and immediate motions are in this second part, cleerly and plainly represented out of the writings of some of their principal, and most approved leaders / published for the common information of such as either really are, or may be, in danger of being insnared and intangled by them by Thomas Hicks.</title>
                  <author>Hicks, Thomas, 17th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 88 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Peter Parker ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. 88.</note>
                  <note>Later reissued as 2nd title in Hicks' Three dialogues between a Christian and a Quaker, London, 1675 (Wing H1926).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Person and offices --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Divinity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Doctrines.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:55411:1"/>
            <p>A CONTINUATION of the DIALOGUE BETWEEN <hi>A Chriſtian and a Quaker:</hi> WHEREIN The truth of thoſe things objected againſt them in the firſt part, are fully confirm'd: TOGETHER With a further account of their perilous and pernitious Errors CONCERNING. The Perſon of Chriſt, His Satisfaction: Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, Sanctification: The miniſtry, and Immediate Motions Are in this Second PART Cleerly and plainly repreſented out of the Writings of ſome of their Principal, and moſt Approved Leaders.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed for the Common Information of ſuch as either really are, or may be, in danger of being Inſnared and intangled by them.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Thomas Hicks.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Tit. 1.10, 11.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>For there are many unruly, and vaintalkers, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivers, whoſe mouthes muſt be ſtopped, who ſubvert whole houſes, teaching things which they ought not, for filthy lucre ſake.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 Tim. 3.9.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>But they ſhall proceed no further, for their folly ſhall be made manifeſt to all men—</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed, for <hi>Peter Parker,</hi> at the <hi>Leg</hi> and <hi>Star</hi> in <hi>Cornhill,</hi> over againſt the <hi>Royal Exchange,</hi> 1673.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:55411:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:55411:2"/>
            <head>The Epiſtle to the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Atan's great deſign againſt Religion is manag'd, and carryed on, partly by er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, and partly by perſecution: by that, he inſtills ſuch notions into the minds of men as may teach them to deny it; by this, he would affright and terrifie them from it. The miſcheifs he hath wrought by the former; the age where into our lot is faln, gives us, but too many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances.</p>
            <p>The people with whom I have to deal, though they are leaſt concerned with, yet pretend to the greateſt intereſt in the truth: who being not ſatisfied with thoſe wayes, and methods, God hath reveal'd, and preſcribed in the holy Scriptures, have broken all bounds, caſt off the yoak, the known rule; and follow only ſuch impulſes, and motions, as hath been given in from him, who deſigns nothing ſhort of their ruine, by ſuch ſtrategems: which are ſo much the more malignant, and effectual towards his intended end, by how much they are more grateful to that proud opinion they have of themſelves.</p>
            <p>Some account of their perillous opinions in, and about ſeveral important points of the Chriſtian Faith, hath heretofore been given unto you: unto which, I have long been threatned with a ſolid Anſwer, though as yet I have not ſeen any: that peice of imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinency, which <hi>G. Whitehead</hi> hath ſent abroad inno the World, I ſuppoſe (though not ſo call'd, yet) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended
<pb facs="tcp:55411:3"/> for an anſwer, wherein, I am rather vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, then anſwered; moſt or all the material things in difference he paſſeth by in ſilence.</p>
            <p>I have, in this ſecond part, preſented you with a more full relation of their dangerous Tenets, wherein the truth of my former Allegations againſt them, are (from their own mouths) fully eſtabliſhed, and all Objections that hitherto have occur'd to my know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, are taken notice of: all which, I ſhall leave to thy ſerious Judgment.</p>
            <p>Many of the things objected againſt them, are ſo Horrid, that 'tis probable ſome will not believe them culpable; God forbid, that I ſhould be guilty of ſuch vile injuſtice, as to charge them with falſe things: examine the quotations, and then judge. As for thoſe inſtances that are not in print, I have ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted evidences of their truth, as may ſatisfie any man.</p>
            <p>From the whole thou may'ſt be inform'd that the Quakers Chriſt, and way of Salvation, is Forreign to what is revealed in the Scriptures. The Doctrines delivered by them are ſuch, as neither themſelves, nor any for them, can give us a diſtinct &amp; intelligible account of. The tendency of all their writings, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarings, doth but lead people into the thickets of ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd, inexplicable, and unintelligible Dotages.</p>
            <p>They amuze us with the great words of <hi>Life and Power,</hi> pretend as if they lived under the immediate Influences, though alas, ſuch is their unhappineſs, <hi>they embrace a cloud, feed on aſhes, and know not that a lye is in their right hand,</hi> and (which is the more aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing) many people (not diſtinguiſhing between words and things, pretences and reall injoyments) are ſo eaſily entrapped and deceived by them: but what ſhall, we ſay, If God for the wantonneſs of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,
<pb facs="tcp:55411:3"/> under the means of Light, <hi>ſhould give them up to a reprobate ſenſe, to ſtrong deluſions to believe lyes, (to follow and admire, ſuch monſters in Religion) that they may be damned, becauſe they received not the Truth in the love of it,</hi> hence when I conſider, that God, to glorifie his Juſtice in puniſhing the wickedneſs of men, doth permit the Enemy to diſtract their minds, and to ſet them on madding after they know not what, on purpoſe to divert them from thoſe things, which are of immediate concernment to them, I ſay, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration hereof leſſens my wonder, when I ſee ſuch deluſions, and impoſtures prevail. Though to ſee a people under the Immediate Judgment of God, fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cying themſelves to be the non-ſuch of the World, for priviledges, and injoyments, is (I confeſſe) matter of deep Lamentation, and Pity.</p>
            <p>'Twill be therefore our intereſt, and Wiſdome, to conſider (before it be too late) both what we do, and who, and what we believe We are haſtning towards Eternity. To miſcarry about our laſt end will not only be unhappy, but it will prove the utmoſt comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our unhappineſs. By nature we are all ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and ſtand guilty before God; if we be unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided of a meet Righteouſneſs wherewith to appear before the great Tribunal, it will be of perilous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence. That a compleat Righteouſneſs ſhould be ſpun out of our own bowells (our lapſ'd condition conſider'd) is impoſſible.</p>
            <p>That Jeſus Chriſt in his Mediatory undertakings for ſinners ſhould be improved by us, is apparently deny'd by theſe Quakers; ſo that all mankind are left (according to their principles) under a fatal neceſſity of periſhing. For, if the way and means, which God's infinite Wiſdom, &amp; Will, hath conſtituted, in order to mans eternal welfare, be rejected; in<gap reason="illegible: torn page" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>in will it be for
<gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:55411:4"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:55411:4"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:55411:5"/> us to think of another. That thus it is, with theſe People, the enſuing Dialogue will give you ſufficient grounds to conclude.</p>
            <p>The perſon of Chriſt they plainly deny, and poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively affirm <hi>That the Doctrine of rejoycing, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance from the works of another is utterly excluded,</hi> W. Pen, Sa. Foun. p. 27. And that <hi>God accepts not any, in whom there is any failing, who do not fulfill the Law and anſwer every demand of Juſtice.</hi> And when they talk of the blood of Chriſt, they delude their hearers or readers. <hi>For, by that blood they mean nothing but the Life and Light within.</hi> At the ſame inſtant they are pleading for Perfection, they will diſcharge you from duty, except you be Immediatly moved thereunto, as if their perfection conſiſted in being ſtocks and ſtones, or, which is worſe, in being rebels againſt the Law of God. Their diſcourſe (for the moſt part) is about the Light within, yet the Light is not more contrary to Darkneſs, than their Dictates are about this thing. What one of them ſaith, another of their own will contradict. What one man at one time affirms, he himſelf will deny at another. One while 'tis the Divine eſſence, 'tis Chriſt, tis increated; another while, 'tis not Chriſt himſelf, but only his gift, or appearance, a ſeed, a meaſure of Light, a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for God. Now, 'tis the only Saviour, and rule; anon we hear of another that both ſaves it, and rules it. Their ſayings hereabouts are ſo croſs and thwart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that 'tis almoſt impoſſible for a man to know when they ſpeak as they think, or think as they ſpeak.</p>
            <p>That every man hath a Light in him, is not denyed: for, had the not a Liggt, he were not capable of being govern'd by a rule: But, that this, which renders him capable of walking by rule, ſhould be it ſelf the rule, is not intelligible.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:55411:5"/>
            <p>The holy Scriptures are eſteemed (by them) infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior to their own pamphlets; yea they render them to be of no more Authority than the Fables of <hi>Eſop.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence they ſubſtitute in its room, their own moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and impulſes, and yet (if you will believe them, when they diſſemble) they will tell you, they own the Scriptures. Their own people know not their intrigues nor the deſigns they have upon them, they do not uſe to truſt (as ſome of them have ſaid) ſuch, (that is their ordinary followers) with their opinions, and yet to ſecure their people to them, they will poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs them with greateſt prejudices imaginable againſt any that ſeriouſly endeavour to recover them, out of their ſnare, ſtill perſwading them to the higheſt vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Quakers Miniſtry, and that whatever is ſuggeſted againſt them, (tho' never ſo true) muſt be looked upon as the greateſt lye. They hate the Light, whilſt they pretend to it: if you diſcourſe with them, 'tis not the argument but the man, they will cheifly be concern'd with; upon whom, can they but fix any thing that is odious, it ſhall paſs both for an anſwer, and a confutation, and to fill up their wickedneſs, they will, (in their ſolemn way, and manner of profaneſs and blaſphemy) bleſs God, that they have thus an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd.</p>
            <p>Obſerve them in their families, the irreligious e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation of their Children, the ordinary neglect of all Chriſtian duties, and alſo their common converſe, and what can we ſee in them, to repreſent them to be what they pretend? They will boaſt of mortification, yet love their backs and bellies to exceſſe, that what will pleaſe their betters, will not content them, and yet ſo infatuated are they, as to conclude themſelves, to be a perfect and ſelf-denying people.</p>
            <p>The Lord in mercy vouchſafe to us in this hour of
<pb facs="tcp:55411:6"/> tryal, wherein the Spirit of error doth ſo fearfully pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail) that his holy truth may ſhine out, to preſerve us from theſe paths of the Deſtroyer, and if it may pleaſe him, to manifeſt, and magnify his Soveraign mercy and Grace in the pardon, and recovery of theſe deluding, and deluded creatures, and grant unto us ſuch an underſtanding of his holy will reveal'd to us, that we may diſcern truth from error; that though Errors and Hereſies do appear and ſhew themſelves, yet we may approve our ſelves ſincere, in a ſerious contending for, and adhering to, the Truth once deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to the Saints.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thomas Hicks.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:55411:6"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A FARTHER ACCOUNT OF THE Dangerous Opinions OF THE QUAKERS: COLLECTED</hi> Out of the Writings of ſeveral of their Principal Leaders, faithfully repreſented in the enſuing Dialogue between a <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> and a <hi>Quaker.</hi>
            </head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>I Have formerly detected you of ſeveral Pernicious Opinions concerning the Scriptures, the Light within, the Perſon of Chriſt, and the Reſurrection of the Dead, &amp;c. which, I preſume, by this time you have conſider'd; What ſay you thereunto?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I ſay the Plagues and Judgments of God will follow thee,</hi> G. Whitehead.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Though your Conſcience might be
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:55411:7"/> touch'd with the evidence of the things alledg'd againſt you, yet it would have been your prudence rather to have diſſembled your Pain, then thus to vent your Paſſion in ſuch furious Replies: But you muſt not think to baffle me with ſuch Sarcaſms, either confeſs the truth of what you are charged with, or elſe diſprove it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I have in print told thee, That thy Dialogue is an unchriſtian forgery,</hi> G. Whitehead, D. Plungd. <hi>Title Page.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Wherein haſt thou proved it ſo to be?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thou haſt preſented the World with a Quaker of thy own forming, making them to ſpeak thoſe impertinencies and falſhoods that were never ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd by any real Quaker; therefore 'tis a forgery,</hi> G. W. <hi>Epiſtle to</hi> D. Pl.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>You had done well, if you had produced ſome inſtances wherein I made them ſpeak what was never utter'd by a real Quaker. But if I can prove that what is ſpoken under that name, is the language of a real Quaker, then thou haſt confeſs'd that ſuch may be guilty of Impertinencies and Falſhoods.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>That thou canſt never prove, for I affirm, That the Quaker there repreſented to the World is of thy own making.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>I wonder that you who pretend ſo much to circumſpection in your Words, ſhould yet be ſo extravagant in Print; 'Tis notorious, the Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue mentions ſeveral that are, and were, appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Quakers, (viz.) <hi>G. Whitehead, G. Fox, James Naylor, Criſp, Richard Hubberthrone,</hi> and <hi>Ben. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley,</hi> &amp;c. If theſe be not, or were not real Quakers, then do you publickly deny it; or if thoſe things
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:55411:7"/> quoted of them be not true, diſprove them: But if that cannot be deny'd, nor this diſproved, how dare you ſay, I have preſented the World with a Quaker of my own making?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I ſay thy Dialogue is no other then un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian forgery.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>That obligeth thee to prove it, which as yet thou haſt not done.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Have I not inſtanc'd in ſeveral particulars wherein thou haſt wronged us,</hi> Dip. Pl. p. 16, 17.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Are thoſe the onely things wherein the forgery conſiſts?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What ſayſt thou to them?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>I tax'd <hi>G. Whitehead,</hi> For affirming <hi>the light within to be God;</hi> And for ſaying, <hi>That the ſpeaking of the Spirit in any is of greater authority then the Scriptures;</hi> and alſo for denying <hi>the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of this Body,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Criſp,</hi> for ſaying, <hi>He knew the beginning and date of that Chriſt I believed in; G. Fox,</hi> for aſſerting, <hi>The Soul to be part of God</hi>'s <hi>Being, to be without beginning, and infinite: Ben. Furly,</hi> for ſaying, 'Tis <hi>the greateſt error in the World that ever was invented, and the ground of all error, To ſay the Scriptures are a Rule to Chriſtians: G. Fox</hi> and <hi>Rich. Hubberthorne</hi> for affirming, That it is dangerous for ignorant people to read the Scriptures, &amp;c. <hi>G. Whitehead</hi>'s ſilence herein, is in my judgment a plain conceſſion touching the verity of theſe Quotations, which is a manifeſt giving away your Cauſe; nevertheleſs, if there be any thing wherein you judge your ſelves wrong'd, let me hear it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thou ſayſt we account the blood of Chriſt no more then a common thing; yea, no more then the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:55411:8"/> blood of a common Thief, this is forgery.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>If the meer light within, and obedience to it, be every way ſufficient to bring every man to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life, as you conſtantly affirm, then the ſhedding of Chriſt's blood upon the Croſs was needleſs, and to no purpoſe. <hi>Iſaac Pennington</hi> (who I ſuppoſe is an approved Quaker) asks this queſtion, Can out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward blood cleanſe? Therefore, ſaith he, We muſt enquire whether it was the blood of the Vail, <hi>that is of the humane nature,</hi> or the blood within the Vail, (viz.) <hi>of that ſpiritual man, conſiſting of Fleſh, Blood, and Bones, which took on him the Vail, or hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature?</hi> 'Tis not the blood of the Vail, that is but outward; and can outward blood cleanſe? if not, then that blood which Chriſt ſhed upon the Croſs, which was the blood of the Humane Nature, is no more then a common thing.</p>
               <p>Secondly, If the ſufferings of Chriſt were only exemplary, as you likewiſe affirm, then what more do you attribute to the blood of Chriſt, then to the blood and ſufferings of other holy perſons?</p>
               <p>Thirdly, If the <hi>myſtery of Iniquity lies in the blood of Chriſt, as</hi> Edw. Billing moſt wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſaid it did, then is the blood of Chriſt, in your eſteem, worſe then the blood of a common Thief: Farther, what ſignifies theſe words which fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently drop from your mouths, <hi>Doſt thou look at Chriſts Death afar off? what will that Blood avail? Didſt ever ſee any of it? That carnal blood, can out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward blood cleanſe? If thou hadſt a great deal of it, would it do thee any good?</hi> Do not theſe Interroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories carry with them an open ſcorn and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of that blood which was ſhed upon the Croſs? conſequently that which is charged upon you is no forgery.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:55411:8"/>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thou ſayſt we make uſe of Scripture onely to ſtop their mouths who call for Scripture proof; this is a Slander.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>If the Scriptures be no Rule; yea, if it be Idolatry to call the Bible a means, as <hi>Whitehead expreſly ſayes it is, D. P. pag.</hi> 13. Who alſo affirms, <hi>That faith grounded on the Scriptures is but an emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Implicit Faith, and be-ſpeaks ſuch perſons void of the Knowledge of God, Chriſt, Salvation, and to be yet in their Sins, and that ſuch men walk by their own Fancies and Imaginations.</hi> Chriſt aſcended, <hi>p.</hi> 11. <hi>Solo Eccleſ.</hi> (a great admirer of <hi>George Fox</hi>) diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſing with a Friend of mine in <hi>London,</hi> told him, The Scriptures were a lye; To whom 'twas replyed, Why then doſt thou mention them? The Quaker anſwer'd, To ſilence thee.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nicolas Lucas,</hi> a real Quaker, was moved to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare his mind thus, (to one I know very well) <hi>Thou mayſt burn thy Bible, and when that is done, thou mayſt ſerve God as well without it; and if thou haſt a mind to have a Scripture, thou mayſt write as good a one thy ſelf.</hi> Many more inſtances might be produced, theſe may ſuffice to acquit me from for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery in this particular; what more haſt thou to ſay?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thou ſayſt that</hi> Fox, Dewsberry, Criſp, Whitehead, <hi>and</hi> Pen, <hi>are exceedingly corrupt in their Morals, herein thou haſt ſpoken falſly.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Haſt thou bid adieu to common honeſty? art thou endeavouring to prove me a Forgerer, and yet at the ſame time be guilty of it thy ſelf? <hi>See the Dialogue, p.</hi> 43. which ſaith, Some of them are exceedingly corrupt in their Morals. If you think it your intereſt to put me on the proof here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:55411:9"/> you may when you pleaſe, and I doubt not (if well) but to give you full ſatisfaction herein, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided that <hi>wilful lying fornication, and adultery may be accounted Immoralities;</hi> what further haſt thou to alledge againſt me?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thou reports that the Quakers deny the reſurrection of the Body, which is falſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>George Whitehead,</hi> in my hearing, before near a hundred Witneſſes, did deny it, in theſe words, <hi>This Body of fleſh and bones ſhall not riſe again;</hi> who alſo ſaith enough in his Pamphlet to acquit me from forgery herein.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thou inſinuates, as if our ſufferings were onely to ſatisfie our Wills and Luſts; herein thou doſt greatly wrong us.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>In this I onely queried what it ſhould be that doth influence you to ſuffer, foraſmuch as you deny that this Body ſhall riſe from the dead, and conſequently can be never the better for what you do or ſuffer. And <hi>G. Fox</hi> maintains, That the Soul is part of Gods Being, &amp;c. and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not capable either of prejudice or advantage, whether you ſuffer or not. Again, is there any people that ever boaſted ſo vainly of their Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings as you do, that ſcarce a Pamphlet can come out from you, but the World muſt hear of your brags in this kind; which can have no other meaning, then to feed that Principle of Pride that reigns in you, and to gain Proſelites to your errors, &amp;c.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thou alſo ſayſt, We deny any eternal ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to be reaped by perſons after death; In this thou doſt abuſe us.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>This is no other then the genuine and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:55411:9"/> direct conſequence of denying the reſurrection of this Body. See 1 Cor. 15.13, 14. <hi>If no reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, then is not Chriſt riſen: If Chriſt be not riſen, then is our preaching vain, and your faith vain, and ye are yet in your Sins,</hi> ver. 17. <hi>Why ſtand I in jeopardy every hour?</hi> ver. 30. <hi>What advantageth me that I have fought with Beaſts at</hi> Epheſus? <hi>Let us eat and drink, for to morrow we dye,</hi> ver. 32.</p>
               <p>If we ask you whether a further happineſs <hi>(then now)</hi> ſhall be injoy'd by the Saints at the laſt day, you will anſwer by another queſtion. <hi>When thinks thou that will be? muſt all the Saints have their hope and faith unanſwer'd till then,</hi> Whitehead <hi>Chriſt aſcended,</hi> p. 34. If we inquire whether you do not wait for any thing further? you will tell us, <hi>That Death and Darkneſs hath power over our Minds, elſe we would never ſhew our ſelves ſuch ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant Papiſts, in putting Salvation ſo far off, till we know not when, according to our carnal conceits,</hi> Whitehead, ibid. If hereupon we ask you, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you injoy eternal life and felicity now? This is your anſwer, <hi>The recompence of reward,</hi> (viz.) <hi>eternal life and felicity is inwardly and ſpiritually received by thoſe that now ſuffer for Chriſt,</hi> White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, ibid. p. 37.</p>
               <p>I ſuppoſe by this time thou art, at leaſt may be ſatisfied, that in theſe inſtances I was not guilty of forgery, and conſequently <hi>Geo. Whitehead</hi>'s pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended anſwer to me carries a manifeſt lye in the front of it, as any may perceive, who compares it with the Dialogue.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I ſay thy Dialogue is proved an unchriſtian forgery.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>It was inconſiderately and imprudently
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:55411:10"/> done by thee to put ſuch words in thy very Title Page, ſince there is nothing in all thy Pamphlet that proves any ſuch thing, but the contrary.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thy Dialogue is not onely a forgery, but it abounds with contradictions.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>This thou ſayſt, though the particulars thou haſt taken notice of evince no ſuch thing: However ſo it hath hapned (though I think not deſignedly by thee) thou haſt fully juſtified that Anſwer in the Catechiſm, p. 72. <hi>You will make your Friends believe, we do nothing but contradict our ſelves:</hi> Waſt thou adviſed and diſcreet herein thus to vindicate me, even whilſt thou art endeavouring to prove me guilty of forgery. But wherein do I contradict my ſelf?</p>
               <p>Will any man (except a Quaker) ſay, That to deny the light within, to be a ſufficient rule to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and yet in ſome caſes appeal to it; and grant it ought to be obey'd, is a contradiction: I verily believe <hi>G. Whitehead</hi> knows not all things, and yet I believe he doth know ſome things, may I not appeal to him concerning that he knows, without being cenſured for contradicting my ſelf; ſurely <hi>G. W.</hi> the contradiction is not in my words, but in thy dark mind.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doſt thou not affirm what any of us have ſaid concerning the light within, is no more then what the Apoſtle ſpeaks of the man of ſin; and may as well prove</hi> Mahomet <hi>to be the true Chriſt, as the light within,</hi> Dip. Pl. pag. 5.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Herein thou doſt onely confute a thing forg'd by thy ſelf, and not utter'd by me: Is this the way to quit thy ſelf from deceit and falſhood, which thou knowſt I have openly accuſed thee of?
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:55411:10"/> The compariſon is not between the light within, and the man of Sin or <hi>Mahomet;</hi> but onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt thoſe Signs and Wonders you boaſt of. And thoſe that <hi>Mahomet,</hi> or the man of Sin, may and do likewiſe pretend unto, ſee the <hi>Dialogue, p.</hi> 11, 12.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thou alſo ſay'ſt, That our obeying the commands of the living Word in us, is no other then a myſtical Romance; Herein thou haſt acted the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane Romancer, and art a moſt irreligious, Miſcreant,</hi> Dip. Pl. p. 5, 6.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>If thou art not condemned in thy own Conſcience for theſe wilful untruths, it will ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie very ill of thee: The <hi>Dialogue</hi> ſpeaks on this wiſe, <hi>p.</hi> 10. you ſay, You own Jeſus Chriſt, but then 'tis with ſuch a mental and myſtical reſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which is no other then a myſtical Romance. Canſt thou think that any ingenious and impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Reader ſhould conceive otherwiſe of thee, then a deceitful and impertinent Scribler. That the Chriſt you own is no other then a myſtical Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance, ſhall be fully proved in this Diſcourſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing.</p>
               <p>As for thoſe other things they are ſo frivolous, that I think them not worthy of any reply, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving that not any man who hath not loſt his reaſon, can conclude as thou doſt. 'Tis one thing to ſay, another thing to prove a man contradicts himſelf; ſuch an Antagoniſt as <hi>G. Whitehead,</hi> cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly was never yet met with, who inſtead of attending to the matters in Controverſie, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends onely with his own Imaginations.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Why ſpeaks thou ſo ſlightly of</hi> George Whitehead, <hi>he is no ſuch impertinent perſon as thou
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:55411:11"/> wouldſt-repreſent him, we know his worth, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>No doubt you have too high a value for him, becauſe you indeed know him not; what ever his errors, deceit, and hypocriſie be, your af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to his Perſon blinds your eyes, that you cannot, or will not ſee it: I muſt tell you, that had I been at his elbow when he was writing the <hi>Dip. Pl.</hi> I could not well have deſired him to write more for my Vindication then he hath done.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Why ſayſt thou ſo?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe the chief things objected againſt you he toucheth not, but manifeſtly falls under the whole charge, as before is hinted.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>This is but thy own imagination.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>I charg'd him for affirming the light within <hi>to be the Divine Eſſence;</hi> and he blames me for ſaying, 'Tis but a meer Creature, <hi>Dip. Pl.</hi> 13. In this then he clears me from any wrong done to him; I accuſe you for denying the Perſon of Chriſt without you, And doth not he ſay, <hi>Chriſt Jeſus a perſon without us is not Scripture language, but the Anthropomorphites and Muggletonians,</hi> Ibid. Why then ſhould it be believed that herein I have wronged either you or him, ſince he himſelf doth ſo fully acquit me: Was not that Anſwer in the <hi>Catechiſm, p.</hi> 73. very pertinent, and truly given in your name. <hi>Though we believe not that you have anſwer'd us, yet you will give it out, you have both anſwer'd and confuted us; and your Friends will believe what you ſay, which is enough to you.</hi> Is not the <hi>Dip. Pl.</hi> calculated onely for the humour of your own Friends; but are you ſo void of reaſon as to think it to be a ſolid anſwer to the <hi>Dialogue?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:55411:11"/>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thou art a Lyar, and doſt thou think that thy particular Election will ſecure thee from the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of lyars,</hi> G. W. Dip. Pl. <hi>Epiſtle.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Thou haſt not proved one lye, neither do I hold ſuch an Election as ſecures perſons guilty of lying, from the reward of lyars. I ſee thou art driven to a ſtrait, that ſince thou canſt not rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onally quarrel with the <hi>Dialogue,</hi> thou ſets up a ſhaddow, a figment of thy own Brain to contend with.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doſt thou not hold a particular election of thy own Party, and but of very few (if any others) beſides, &amp;c.</hi> G. Whitehead.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>I perceive thy Dictates are not infallible, for as thou haſt not declared thy own, ſo neither haſt thou written (nor indeed doſt thou know) my belief in this matter: But what is all this to the <hi>Dialogue,</hi> why art thou concern'd ſo much about Election, who believes no ſuch thing of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, either abſolute or conditionals; that Election you generally hold, is onely of the Seed, which is Chriſt himſelf; therefore thou doſt but trifle, and fill up paper to no purpoſe; might it not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore have been of more advantage to your Cauſe, if <hi>William Penn</hi> had concern'd himſelf in the exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of the Dialogue (as I expected he would). That what <hi>G. Whitehead</hi> could not do in his dull method and manner of reaſoning, 'tis probable <hi>William Penn,</hi> with his Confidence and Rhetorique, might have done.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What real Quaker ever ſpoke thus, that they who will not believe our ſayings, we will not ſpare to condemn, and ſtigmatize them, and it concerns us to render them as ridiculous as we can.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:55411:12"/>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>If you would have nothing charged upon you but what is indeed utter'd by approved Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, whether it might not be neceſſary to give us a Catalogue of the Names of ſuch; or if you think not meet to do this, then to give us ſome certain intelligible Character how a real Quaker may be known; may that paſs for a Character which <hi>Tho. Ruddyer</hi> gave in my hearing, viz. <hi>One that is come to the pure Language, to ſpeak thee and and thou;</hi> then your Objection will be eaſily an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd: Doth not one of your own tell us, that 'tis your manner to render ſuch odious, and the more effectually to weaken their Teſtimonies, you will fix upon them ſcurrilous and contemptible Appellations: And do not all men that know you, know this is true. But that I may fully ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie you in this point, I ask whether <hi>Edward Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughs</hi> was not an approved Quaker?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yea, he was endued with the Almighty Power of God, which lived and reigned in him: This his own Works will in a large meaſure teſtifie the truth of, a man able to ſtop the mouths of all Gain-ſayers; This is my teſtimony to this man of God, who hath been a bleſſing to the Lord in his Generation,</hi> Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah Coale, his <hi>Epiſtle</hi> before <hi>Edw. Burroughs</hi> his Works in <hi>Folio.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Was this <hi>Joſiah Coale</hi> a real Quaker?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>He was ſo.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>In what reſpect did the Almighty Power of God live and raign in him; and how was he a bleſſing to the Lord, for I muſt confeſs I do not well underſtand the meaning of this teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>'Tis no matter for anſwering ſuch cavilling Queſtions.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:55411:12"/>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Who elſe gives their Teſtimony to <hi>Edw. Burroughs</hi> and his Works.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theſe memorable Works of</hi> Edw. Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughs (printed for the good of Generations to come, 1672.) <hi>is brought forth for us, and our Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and ſuch as are moderate, and well affected; greater deſires hereof could not be in any, then in my own particular, I having travelled both to anſwer and ſerve the truth, and the deſires of Friends herein; Let none condemn the honeſt plainneſs and harmleſs ſimplicity of any of his firſt Works here inſerted, for many are living Witneſſes that the Power and Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God did then appear and ſhew it ſelf through ſuch plainneſs and ſimplicity, to the confounding of the wiſdom of many that ſeemed high and lofty. And thus, dear Friends, as the Salvation of our dear Brother</hi> Edw. Burroughs, <hi>according to his deſire, whilſt in the Body, I recommend this Volume of his Books, being therein the Truths, and your Servant</hi> Ellis Hooks. See the Epiſtle Dedicatory to the Quakers.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Of what uſe and ſervice do you judge theſe Works may be to you, and to your Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>It may not be unneceſſary for Friends and Children to read and peruſe theſe Teſtimonies, Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations, and Vindications of Truth, where they are in a way of Controverſie given forth; the reading whereof may be of ſervice to them, they being in the light and inſpiration of the Almighty, from which all Scriptures, or Writings, that are given forth, are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to the man of God for his accommodation; for though many of you are come to a particular ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the true Light, and know ſo much of Chriſt, ſo as
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:55411:13"/> to dye for him, yet cannot ſo well diſpute for him: Though that be neceſſary, and few given up and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed for that Service; therefore there may be need for more to apply their hearts to wiſdom,</hi> Ellis Hooks, <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>If written Teſtimonies and Vindications be profitable to the Man of God, for his accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modation, to help him to Diſpute, as you plainly intimate: Doth not this interfere with that grand Notion of yours, which ſaith, You muſt do all <hi>by the immediate motion of the power within.</hi> But if the Light and Power which you and your Children have be not ſufficient of it ſelf to accompliſh you for this Service <hi>of Diſputation for, and vindicating of that you call the Truth,</hi> why then do you contend ſo much for its All-ſufficiency? me-thinks you who pretend to infallibility, ſhould be very careful to make one ſtory agree with another, and not thus to be taken in different tales, to the manifeſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paragement both of your ſelves and Opinions. But is this <hi>Ellis Hooks</hi> a true Quaker?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thou needſt not doubt that, foraſmuch as be was imploy'd in that Service, for the collecting and printing theſe Works of</hi> Edw. Burroughs, <hi>and alſo allow'd to prefix his Epiſtle before it. And there are others, who were and are in the Miniſtry, that hath given their Teſtimony to this Servant and Prophet of the Lord, as thou mayſt ſee in their Epiſtles before his Works.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Shall Dayes, Moneths, and Years, wear out thy Name? Shall not thy noble and valiant Acts which thou haſt wrought through the Power of him that ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated thee from the Womb, live in Generations to come? The Children yet unborn ſhall have thee
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:55411:13"/> in their mouths, and thy Works ſhall teſtifie of thee in Generations that yet have no Being, and ſhall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count thee bleſſed: When I think of thee, I am melted into tears of ſorrow, becauſe of the want that the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance of the Lord hath of thee.</hi> Francis How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gill.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>As for</hi> Edw. Burroughs <hi>our dear Brother and Companion in travel, ſuffering, and conſolation for the everlaſting Goſpels ſake, his Teſtimony lives with us; He was a Preacher of Righteouſneſs, one who travell'd for the Redemption of the Creature from under the bondage of Corruption. The name of this Miniſter of Righteouſneſs is written in the Lambs Book of Life,</hi> George Whitehead; <hi>His name is chronicled in the Lambs Book of Life, a righteous Plant, a valiant Warrier, more then a Conquerer; who is dead, but yet liveth amongſt us, and amongſt us is alive,</hi> George Fox.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Being well aſſured from theſe Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies that <hi>Edw. Burroughs</hi> was an approved Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker; then for the ſatisfaction of you and others in this Point, whether I have feigned a Quaker, as <hi>Whitehead</hi> ſuggeſts, or made them ſpeak other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then in their own proper Dialect. I ſhall tranſcribe twenty queſtions, which I find <hi>printed in the memorable Works of</hi> Edw. Burroughs, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the force and import of his Anſwers to each Queſtion, as you will find, if you conſult his Works in <hi>Folio,</hi> printed 1672. wherein the Spirit and Principles of the Quakers is not a little laid open. The queſtions were propounded (as that Book informs me) by one <hi>Philip Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Q.</hi> Whether the Word was made Fleſh more or oftner then once?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:55411:14"/>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>In this Quere thou are manifeſted what thou art, where thou art, and what ſpirit thou art of, a Reprobate, a Child of Darkneſs: In this Quere thy ſpirit is ſeen and known in the eternal light; thou knoweſt not what thou askeſt, thy Quere comes from thy dark polluted mind: Thou art a ſtranger to the Life, without God in the World; the Light condemns thee, and all thy generation eternally. The Word made Fleſh we witneſs, which dwells amongſt us, and we behold his Glory, whereby we witneſs thee and all thy generation to be in the ſorcery and witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft; the light in thee will tell thee ſo, to which thou muſt be obedient before thou canſt witneſs the Word made Fleſh onc't, for thou art darkneſs it ſelf; when thou canſt witneſs the Word made Fleſh onc't, then thou wilt know whether the Son of God was made of a Woman more or oftner then onc't: But thou Dragon that would devour the Man-Child, thou the Dragon with thy Angels art caſt into the Earth. For thy other nineteen Queres thou haſt conjured them up in the Black Art, out of the bottomleſs Pit,</hi> Edw. Burrough's Works in Folio, p. 29, 30.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Was ever Queriſt ſo rudely and uncivilly treated? or was ever queſtion thus ridiculouſly anſwer'd? was this the honeſt plainneſs and harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſ. ſimplicity of this man? and was this his ſilen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing all Oppoſers? Is there any thing in the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion to provoke to ſuch Bedlam Rhetorick? to call a man Reprobate, Child of Darkneſs, a ſtranger to the Life, without God in the World; yea, and to damn him eternally, only for a modeſt and ſober enquiry; was this his valour for the Lamb? what means he by witneſſing the Word made Fleſh? Is it any thing more then the Seed, Light,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:55411:14"/> or Power within? But is this to the queſtion? Doth the Scripture by the Word being made Fleſh, intend onely the Light within? ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thouſands (that in all things walk not up to the light in them) do believe that the Word was made Fleſh onc't, contrary to the bold aſſertion of this man, <hi>That they muſt be obedient to the Light within, before they can witneſs</hi> (or believe) <hi>this thing.</hi> 'Tis eaſie to gueſs what your notions are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Word made Fleſh; <hi>Burroughs</hi> ſaith, the Queriſt is <hi>darneſs it ſelf;</hi> if ſo, then ſurely he had no light in him to tell him he was in the ſorcery and witchcraft; If no light, how is your opinion true, That every man hath Chriſt, or his light in him; is it poſſible for that man <hi>(in whom Chriſt or his Light is)</hi> to be darkneſs it ſelf? And how could he be obedient to the light within, if he had none to obey.</p>
               <p>Again, is a ſerious propoſal about the Word being made Fleſh onc't, an argument of one being in the ſorcery and witchcraft? O ſtupendious madneſs and folly! And if the Queriſt be the Dragon, and hath his Angels, I would willingly know (of ſome of them who have commended his memorable Works to the Ages to come) who or what theſe Angels are?</p>
               <p>And ſince he hath already doom'd and paſs'd ſentence upon the reſt of the Queres, as being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jured in the Black Art out of the bottomleſs Pit; we may plainly foreſee what Anſwers they are like to be attended with, nevertheleſs I ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed.</p>
               <p n="2">(2. <hi>Q.</hi>) Whether did the man Chriſt, ſlain (in reſpect of God's Decree and efficacy) from the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:55411:15"/> foundation of the World, really and indeed, ſuffer death as upon the Croſs at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> more or oftner then once?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>In this Quere thou Diviner art found ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Scriptures the Divination of thy own Brain, whereupon the Plagues of God are to be added to thee: Oh thou lyar, where doth the Scriptures ſpeak as thou ſpeaks here? But in the light thou art ſeen, and art for the condemnation: The man Chriſt we own, and witneſs, and the Lambs Book of life, which was ſlain from the foundation of the World; we witneſs the Lamb of God, and thee to be the Beaſt that makes war with the Lamb, and thou Antichriſt, which looks at Chriſts death at</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>alone; ſo let all thy Congregation ſee what they hold up that follows thee,</hi> Edw. Burroughs, ibid. p. 30.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Can any man be the wiſer for this An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer? Is it Antichriſtian to look at Chriſt's death at <hi>Jeruſalem?</hi> Doth the man Chriſt die in you? and muſt he be onely look'd at as ſo dying? The queſtion is plain, whether the man Chriſt did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſuffer death as upon the Croſs more then onc't? though <hi>Edw. Burroughs</hi> ſaith, 'Twas con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jured up in the Black Art, and accordingly in his canting way anſwers, We witneſs the Lamb of God: But what is this witneſſing to the point? or is Diviner, Lyar, and Beaſt, a fit reply to ſo harmleſs an enquiry; I ſee, though you cannot, or will not anſwer a queſtion in plain and intelligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible terms; yet you can and will freely curſe and damn the Queriſt. And whilſt you pretend to own and witneſs the Man Chriſt, &amp;c. you ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently intimate your erronious thoughts con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Sufferings of Chriſt upon the Croſs,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:55411:15"/> though you are aſhamed or afraid to ſpeak them out.</p>
               <p n="3">(3. <hi>Q.</hi>) Whether did the Man Chriſt really and indeed ſuffer in his own Perſon for that end, and after the ſame manner which he did upon the Croſs at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> before that time or ſince that time?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Here thou full of all ſubtilty, haſt manifeſted thy poyſon and enmity; but thou art ſeen with the Light, and with it condemn'd for ever: Chriſt Jeſus in his own Perſon doth, and ever did ſuffer by thee, and ſuch as thou art, after the ſame manner: Thou blind Phariſee and Blaſphemer, wouldſt thou have Chriſt have more ends in ſuffering then one,</hi> Ibid. p. 30.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Whether there be more poyſon and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity manifeſted in the Queſtion, or in the Anſwer, I leave others to judge: Was Chriſt indeed actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally crucified upon the Croſs by the Queriſt? and doth Chriſt alwayes ſuffer after the ſame manner, and for the ſame end, as he did when crucified at <hi>Jeruſalem?</hi> If ſo, <hi>How is the Body of Jeſus Chriſt ſaid to be offer'd once for all? And why is it call'd an offering of one Sacrifice,</hi> Heb. 10.10, 12, 14. Be free and plain, let us know whether you do believe that Chriſt did, and doth ſuffer in his own perſon for the ſame end, and after the ſame manner as he did upon the Croſs, both before that time, and ſince that time, or deny it; elſe ſay, you cannot, or that 'tis not convenient to give a poſitive an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer.</p>
               <p n="4">(4. <hi>Q.</hi>) Was not that death which the Man Chriſt ſuffer'd once, and but once, upon the Croſs at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> ſo ſatisfactory for all the Sins of the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:55411:16"/> Elect, as that the juſtice of God, did not, doth not require any ſuffering or working upon that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, either from Sinner or Saint?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Here thou Jeſuite art pleading for a Chriſt afar off thee, that Chriſt which died at</hi> Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem <hi>did not ſatisfie for thee, who art an enemy to him, and art under the woe, and from that woe thou ſhalt never flee. The death of the Man Chriſt we own, and witneſs; The ſame Chriſt that ſuffer'd, we witneſs made manifeſt. And here thou lyar, art made manifeſt to be a lyar, who ſaid, We deny that Chriſt which died at</hi> Jeruſalem; <hi>ſo let thy mouth be ſtopt thou lyar, who art for the lake: And whereas thou queries, whether the juſtice of God be not ſatisfied for the Sins of the Elect; let ſhame ſtrike thee in the face, that thou ſhould take upon thee to ſpeak to any people, and knoweſt not the Scripture: where reads thou, that God requires ſatisfaction for the Sins of the Elect, or laid any thing to their Charge; Let all peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſee whether thou be not a blind ignorant ſot,</hi> Ibid. p. 30, 31.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>It ſeems by this Anſwer, 'tis Jeſuitical to plead for that Chriſt which died at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> which <hi>Burroughs</hi> calls a Chriſt afar off: Then in what ſenſe muſt you be underſtood, when you ſay, You own the ſame Chriſt that ſuffer'd? If the death of the ſame man you do truly (and without reſerved meanings) acknowledge, why do you ſtigmatize the Queriſt for pleading for that Chriſt? The Queriſt is accuſed for a lyar, for ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, You deny that Chriſt which died at <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> and yet <hi>Edw. Burroughs calls him Jeſuit, for pleading for a Chriſt afar off;</hi> Is not this to acquit his Accuſer, and plainly to condemn himſelf for a
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:55411:16"/> raſh and peeviſhman. That <hi>Burroughs</hi> did really lye and diſſemble in his pretences to own the ſame Chriſt, doth in part appear in his Anſwer, and will more fully in the ſequel of this Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue.</p>
               <p>How did this Quaker know, that Chriſt did not ſatisfie for the Queriſt, and that he was under that woe, from which he ſhould not eſcape? What means he by the Elect, for whom no ſatisfaction is required? and to whoſe charge nothing is laid? was not Chriſt's death for Sin? then either for the ſins of the Elect, or for the ſins of others; not for the Elect, nor for the Queriſt; for whoſe ſins then? 'Tis evident enough, he intended 'twas onely <hi>for the Seed, which Seed is Chriſt;</hi> ſo that Sinners are no wayes concern'd in the Sufferings of Jeſus Chriſt, unleſs you will ſay, <hi>That Chriſt in man is a Sinner:</hi> O the pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and forbearance of God, that ſhould bear with ſuch Blaſphemies as theſe are; that ever men pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to infallible Teachings, ſhould ſo render the Doctrine of Jeſus Chriſt, and his Sufferings, as to expoſe them to the greateſt ſcorn and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt.</p>
               <p n="5">(5. <hi>Q.</hi>) Whether you be reconciled to God by any other Obedience, then that very Obedience which Chriſt perform'd in his own Perſon, or by any ſuffering or death then that which Chriſt ſuffer'd upon the Croſs at <hi>Jeruſalem?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Silence Fleſh, wouldſt thou who art an enemy to God, know how we are reconciled to God, and by what Obedience; own the light in thy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and be obedient to that, then thou ſhalt know by what Obedience we are reconciled to God: For yet
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:55411:17"/> thou knoweſt no Obedience, but art an enemy to the Croſs of Chriſt, and in the myſtery of Iniquity, and in the dark power of the Man of Sin: What haſt thou to do to talk of Obedience, thou art blind; and in the broad way that leads to Death,</hi> Ibid. p. 31.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Is this to give a reaſon of your Hope with meekneſs and fear? Suppoſe the Queriſt as igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant as his Anſwerer would repreſent him, ought he not to have endeavoured his Information; the queſtion doth deſerve a better reply then here is given to it; what inconvenience can there be in giving a ſerious and ſolid account, how we are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to God? Was not <hi>Edw. Burroughs</hi> either aſhamed or afraid to ſpeak out what that Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is by which you are reconciled. <hi>William Penn,</hi> I muſt confeſs, herein is more free and inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious with us, He confidently affirms, <hi>Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by that Righteouſneſs which Chriſt fulfil'd in his own Perſon without us, is a Doctrine of Devils,</hi> Apolog. p. 148. I doubt not but <hi>Burroughs</hi> was of the ſame mind, though he kept it ſecret from the Queriſt as much as in him lay: Hitherto you ſee we have not one direct Anſwer to any Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion.</p>
               <p n="6">(6. <hi>Q.</hi>) Whether did not the Man Chriſt ſuffer as a publick Perſon in the Elects ſtead, or in their behalf, and for that end, That none who believed in him might die eternally?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thou blind Guide makes it manifeſt, that thou knowſt not the Man Chriſt at all, nor his Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; A publick Perſon he is, not to thee, but a my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery thou knows nothing of; and for the redeeming of the Elect from under ſuch mouths as thine, Chriſt did
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:55411:17"/> and doth ſuffer, and thoſe that believe, deny ſuch dumb idol Shepherds as thee,</hi> Ibid. p. 31.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Still nothing but Impertinent Ravings, inſtead of a direct Anſwer? What doth the <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker</hi> intend by the Man Chriſt, and his Sufferings, which he ſaith the Queriſt knows not at all? Is Chriſt a publick Perſon or not? did he die for this end, That all who believe in him might not die eternally, or did he not? who, or what is the Elect that is under the mouths of ſuch as the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt? for the redeeming of whom Chriſt did and doth ſuffer: And what is that which Chriſt doth now ſuffer for the Redemption of the Elect? and what that Bondage is from which he redeems? And what is meant by believing? and in whom? Is it in that Perſon who ſuffer'd upon the Croſs? or the Light within? Do not equivocate, but 2ſpeak to the Point directly, whether that Perſon that is diſtinct from all other perſons; He that was in the World, and died upon the Croſs, roſe again, and is now at the right hand of God, be that very Chriſt we are to believe in? or that it is not our Duty and Intereſt ſo to do, but meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to believe in, and obey the light within, as the onely Mediator between God and Sinners. Let us know your minds herein in down-right terms, and do not put us off with your witneſſings, which to us ſignifie nothing.</p>
               <p n="7">(7. <hi>Q.</hi>) Whether the Sufferings of Chriſt, now in his Saints, be all the ſatisfaction that is made to, or which the juſtice of God looks for, for ſins paſts, preſent, and to come?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thou Blaſphemer askeſt thou knows not what, Is not Chriſt the ſame as ever? and is not the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:55411:18"/> Sufferings of Chriſt ſatisfactory where ever? what will ſatisfie, if the Sufferings of Chriſt will not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie? Let all people take notice what a Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer thou art, or what can they learn from ſuch as thee, who knows neither the Juſtice of God, nor the Sufferings of Chriſt in his Saints,</hi> Ibid. p. 31.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>In anſwer to the fourth Queſtion, <hi>this Quaker</hi> deny'd the Sufferings of Chriſt to be <hi>ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factory either for the Elect or others,</hi> and here he grants his Sufferings are ſatisfactory where-ever, but tells us not to whom, nor for whom they are ſo: And whereas he talks of Chriſt's Sufferings in his Saints, I would quere, whether his Sufferings in that ſenſe be all the ſatisfaction that is made to, or which the Juſtice of God requires? Again, it may not be amiſs to obſerve a little the <hi>policy of this man,</hi> who, that he might the better hide, and prevent any ſuſpition of himſelf being a Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, he indites and arraigns the Queriſt as ſuch, perfectly in this, imitating the Devil, who will charge upon another his own fault; that thus it is, conſider the Quakers Opinion of Chriſt in his Saints, which is, <hi>'tis God, and his eternal Power;</hi> but doth God and his Power Suffer and die in his Saints? <hi>Is this to exalt the Deity of the Son of God</hi> (which ſometimes you pretend to do) to make him ſubject to death, and to death in you; but pray, how can an immortal, immutable Spirit die, and in what ſenſe is ſuch a death ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factory? But the miſery is, ask what queſtion we will, in the plaineſt terms we can, the Quakers will anſwer equivocally, and not let us know their minds (as one of them ſaid, <hi>We do not uſe to truſt ſuch with our Opinions</hi>) as if they were
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:55411:18"/> aſhamed to own the things themſelves be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve.</p>
               <p n="8">(8. <hi>Q.</hi>) Whether was not that Body of Jeſus which was offer'd upon the Croſs at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the one and onely Sacrifice for Sin God accepted, to which all the Saints did, and do look to be ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified without any other Works?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Here thou replyes thy ſottiſh Queries, which riſes out of thy dark mind, concerning the Body of Jeſus, as the Devil did about the body of</hi> Moſes; <hi>let thy mouth be ſtopt, for the Body of Jeſus thou knowſt not, nor what it conſiſts on; and the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering of it up, thou knowſt nothing of; Thou art none of the Saints, but without in the World, for thee the Body of Chriſt is no ſatisfaction: And thou Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, what haſt thou to do to talk of believing, that is the condition of the Saints, whoſe Works thou knowſt not; Thou diſobedient one, upon whom God. will render Vengeance in flaming fire,</hi> Ibid. p. 32.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Oh the rudeneſs and unworthineſs of this Anſwerer, who took no farther notice of the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, then to vent his rancour and ſpleen againſt the Queriſt: <hi>Surely the venome of Aſps was under this mans tongue.</hi> 'Tis to be bewail'd, that a ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous queſtion concerning that one and onely Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, Chriſt offer'd, ſhould be parallel'd <hi>with the Devils contending about the body of</hi> Moſes; and that ſuch <hi>who will be diſputing about the Body of Jeſus,</hi> muſt be branded for Reprobates (<hi>Naylors Love to the loſt,</hi> p. 57. <hi>Printed</hi> 1656.) Had it not been better to have condemn'd ſuch Dictates as theſe to perpetual Oblivion, then to print them for the Generations to come? And foraſmuch as he ſaith, what the Body of Jeſus conſiſts of, and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:55411:19"/> the offering of it up, the Queriſt knew nothing of, 'tis evident he intends another body then that which he took of the Virgin, but what that is, he acquaints us not.</p>
               <p n="9">(9. <hi>Q.</hi>) Whether there be any other Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, by which Chriſt the Saints are juſtified in the ſight of God, then that which Works in them and by them?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thou art accurſed, and made manifeſt, who preacheth another Goſpel, and wouldſt have ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Righteouſneſs then that of Chriſt: Thou Beaſt, to whom the Plagues of God are due, upon whom the Wrath of God muſt be accompliſhed, who would have another Righteouſneſs then that which Chriſt works in the Saints, and by them; Thou wouldſt be juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and live in thy ſin, but thou art ſhut out from God for ever; we witneſs Juſtification by Faith,</hi> Ibid. p. 32.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>There is nothing in the queſtion impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting another Righteouſneſs, then that of Chriſts; was it not then more then enough for him to cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and damn the Queriſt, but muſt he needs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuate a wilful lye to compleat his wickedneſs, that the Quakers, and their Children may be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſht for diſpute, and know how to anſwer their Oppoſers, as <hi>Ellis Hooks intimates in his Epiſtle. Burroughs</hi> ſaith, We witneſs Juſtification by Faith, which is no other then your uſual can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, neither doth it in any wiſe conclude the queſtion: Indeed, when he calls the <hi>Queriſt Beaſt,</hi> upon whom the wrath of God muſt be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed, becauſe he would (as the Quaker imagines) have another Righteouſneſs, then that which Chriſt works in the Saints, and by them.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:55411:19"/> Herein, I muſt confeſs, he plainly denies that there is any other Righteouſneſs, and conſequently all that Chriſt did and ſuffered without us, is utterly unconcern'd in this buſineſs of Juſtification, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly repugnant to <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.18, 19. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.5, 11.</p>
               <p n="10">(10. <hi>Q.</hi>) Whether doth Sanctification or Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification in order antecede holineſs of life, or Juſtification by Faith go before; or whether doth not God love man, ere man lov'd God?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Here thou dark blind Hypocrite haſt ſhut out thy ſelf from the knowledge of God in any mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: Oh that people ſhould be ſo blind, as to look to learn any thing of ſuch as thee but Sin and Filthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; what haſt: thou been teaching, that neither knows Juſtification nor Sanctification, but art que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring which goes before: Let all people Judge whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou be not a Teacher of laſciviouſneſs, ſin, and uncleanneſs. How dareſt thou mention a holy life? thou man which art</hi> Cain, <hi>God doth not love nor ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept thee, nor thy Sacrifice; and for Juſtification by Faith, thou knowſt nothing of it, which we own and witneſs,</hi> Ibid. p. 32.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Was this the plainneſs and ſimplicity through which (you ſay) he did confound the wiſdom of the high and lofty? was this your dear Brother in the Lord? <hi>as George Whitehead calls him.</hi> 'Tis too apparent he was under the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, rule, and government of a moſt wicked, lying, and reviling Spirit. Can any man or men conclude the Queriſt to be a Teacher of Laſcivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, meerly for asking, whether Sanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Juſtification do not in order go before holineſs of life? Certainly the Children yet
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:55411:20"/> unborn, if they ſhould ſee theſe his Works, will have him in their mouths as a moſt ridiculous, impertinent, and railing perſon.</p>
               <p n="11">(11. <hi>Q.</hi>) Whether the Juſtice of God be fully ſatisfied for all the ſins of the Elect, ere Chriſt appear to their Souls, or holineſs appear in their Lives?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Here thou full of all ſubtilty art compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended, and with the light of Chriſt thou art ſeen, and with the life thou art judg'd and condemn'd: Who would lay Sin to the charge of the Elect, thou Sorcerer, doth the Elect of God ſin? ſhall the Elect die? To that in thy Conſcience I ſpeak,</hi> Ibid. p. 32.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>If the Elect of God neither do, <hi>nor never did ſin;</hi> 'tis meet we ſhould know who or what is meant by the Elect: who ſhall lay any thing to the charge of the Elect? <hi>'tis God that juſtifies, who ſhall condemn? 'tis Chriſt that died,</hi> Rom. 8.33, 34. If by the Elect be intended per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, then either they are or were Sinners; but if by the Elect you mean <hi>a meer Principle, Spirit, or ſeed in man:</hi> Then I ask you, How God is ſaid to juſtifie that? and in what ſenſe did Chriſt die for this Seed? If Juſtification do ſuppoſe a guilt, I quere in what reſpect this ſpirit or ſeed in man may be ſaid to be guilty? If you ſay, It ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver did, nor doth Sin, how then doth God juſtifie it? and what neceſſity was there of Chriſt's dying for that which was perfectly ſinleſs? <hi>To that</hi> (as thy phraſe is) <hi>in thy Conſcience do I now ſpeak.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="12">(12. <hi>Q.</hi>) Whether the holy Lives and Works of the Saints be not excluded from the act of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:55411:20"/> Juſtification from the guilt of Sin?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thou dead Beaſt, thou art a ſtranger from the life of God, and is excluded from the holy life of the Saints, and their works, Thou art unredeemed from thy vain Converſation, ☞ and ſo art not juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, nor never ſhall be: And by the ſame that the Saints are juſtified, thou art condemn'd into the lake for ever,</hi> Ibid. p. 32, 33.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>This anſwer (like the reſt) is full of pride, rage, and folly; who will believe that Teſtimony which you moſt unadviſedly have given of this man, That he was a faithful Servant and Prophet of the Lord: Did ever any foame out their own ſhame more then this <hi>your pretended Prophet,</hi> who impudently aſſumes to himſelf the authority of <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termining the eternal condition of the Queriſt;</hi> tells him, ☞ He neither is, <hi>nor never ſhall be juſtified;</hi> may it not be with reſpect to this curſing and railing humour, which was predominant in him, That you call him a Son of Thunder. But whether <hi>Edw. Burroughs</hi> hath ſpoken any thing pertinently, and properly to the queſtion, I ſhall leave it to others, yea <hi>to that in thy Conſcience</hi> to judge.</p>
               <p n="13">(13. <hi>Q.</hi>) Whether that Righteouſneſs which is wrought by the Saints be every way anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Juſtice of God?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>There again thy blindneſs is made mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt; Is there any Righteouſneſs but that of Chriſt Jeſus? and is not that every way anſwerable to the juſtice of God? But ſuch polluted filthy Beaſts as thou wouldſt have another Righteouſneſs; but thy Righteouſneſs we deny, and the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt we witneſs, which ſhall be reveal'd on thee in flames of fire,</hi> Ibid. p. 33.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:55411:21"/>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Did ever man pretending <hi>(I will not ſay to perfection or infallibility, but)</hi> to reaſon or modeſty, reply at this rate? Did every queſtion affright him, and put him into ſuch a conſternation, as that he could expreſs himſelf no otherwiſe then like one perfectly mad. There is not the leaſt intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in any of the foregoing queſtions aſſerting <hi>any other Righteouſneſs</hi> but that of Chriſt's, and yet this wretched man had the confidence to ſay, Such filthy Beaſts (as he was pleas'd to account the Queriſt) would have another Righteouſneſs. Art not thou aſhamed of this injuſtice and lying, which thy dear <hi>Brother Edw. Burroughs</hi> was guilty of? to talk of your witneſſing the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, is no more but your common and idle prating, and nothing to the point in queſtion: Muſt we be concluded onely by what you igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly and impudently ſay you witneſs?</p>
               <p n="14">(14. <hi>Q.</hi>) Whether none be accounted righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in the ſight of God, in whom is any corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or failing, or who do not fulfil the Law, and anſwer every demand of Juſtice?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Here thou polluted Beaſt makes it mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt what thou haſt been driving at all this while, which is, that thou wouldſt have thy corruption and filthineſs to be accounted righteous in God's ſight, that ſo thou mayſt wallow in thy filthineſs: But</hi> John <hi>ſaith, He that commits ſin is of the Devil; The Son of God was manifeſted, that he might de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the works of the Devil, and thou man of Sin wouldſt have it ſtand; ☞ God doth not accept any where there is any failing, or who do not fulfil the Law, and anſwer every demand of Juſtice,</hi> Ibid. p. 33.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:55411:21"/>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>This queſtion (I do confeſs) hath the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of a direct and poſitive anſwer, though it be introduced <hi>with his wonted railing, together with a wilful lye;</hi> certainly had not <hi>Edw. Burroughs</hi> been deſperate, and utterly deſtitute of any ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous reſpect either to God or man, or his own credit, he durſt not have attempted to fix ſo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious an untruth upon the <hi>Queriſt,</hi> as that he would have corruption and filthineſs to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted righteous in God's ſight: There is not any thing of ſuch an import in the queſtion, which is not whether failing and corruption may be accounted righteous, but whether none in whom is any failing or corruption may be ſo; cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption and failing is one thing, the perſon in whom it may be is another.</p>
               <p>But to his anſwer, ☞ <hi>God accepts not any who do not fulfil the Law, and anſwer every demand of Juſtice;</hi> If ſo, woe be to you Quakers, as well as to any others, for certainly you cannot be ſaved according to this Principle; you are far (how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever you flatter your ſelves) from fulfilling the Law, and anſwering every demand of Juſtice; with <hi>Edw. Burroughs</hi> agrees another of your Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, namely <hi>William Penn, Sandy Foundation,</hi> p. 29, 30.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obedience to Juſtification</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ought to be as perſonally extenſive, as was mans Diſobedience to Condemnation; in which real (not imputative) ſenſe thoſe various terms of Sanctification, Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Reſurrection, Life, Redemption, Juſtification,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>are moſt infallibly underſtood; for impute or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting ſignifies no more in Scriptures, but to expreſs men really and perſonally to be that which is imputed
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:55411:22"/> to them, whether as guilty, or remitted. For</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>any to be juſtified from the imputation of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Righteouſneſs, is both rediculous and dangerous; whence came that uſual ſaying amongſt many Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of Religion, That God looks not upon them as they are in themſelves, but as they are in Chriſt.</hi> Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the drift and ſcope <hi>of Penns</hi> Diſcourſe, this uſual ſaying muſt come from the <hi>conceivings of the dark imputarians of this Age:</hi> But I muſt tell Mr. <hi>Penn</hi> whatever his deluded fancy may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning himſelf, miſerable will be his condition, <hi>if God do look upon him onely, as he is in himſelf:</hi> The time will come he may curſe the day that ever he entertain'd ſuch an opinion, or that it was his ſad lot <hi>to fall amongſt ſuch a people,</hi> who render Jeſus Chriſt in all his undertakings for Sinners, no more then a meer cipher. For ſaith <hi>Edw. Burroughs, ☞ God will not accept of any who do not fulfil the Law, and anſwer every demand of Juſtice.</hi> O ye wretched men, that ſhould in ſuch a day and Nation, have the face to utter ſuch a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine as this is, which caſheers the whole Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, and turns it out of doors.</p>
               <p n="15">(15. <hi>Q.</hi>) Whether a Soul be juſtified before God by the non-imputation of Sin, and the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt's Perſon to his Faith, or by a Righteouſneſs wrought by Chriſt in the perſon juſtified, or to be juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Stop thy mouth thou Sorcerer, which art gathering up a heap of confuſion, fit for nothing but to be turn'd into the bottomleſs pit; wherein thou talks of imputation and non-imputation, and of a perſon juſtified and to be juſtified. Thy language is
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:55411:22"/> the language of</hi> Egypt, <hi>and in the myſtery of Iniquity, which is condemn'd into the lake of Perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by the light of Chriſt: I own no Righteouſneſs but what is of Chriſt, and is wrought by him; which Righteouſneſs ſhall confound thee, and all thy un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs and conjurations, the ſame that juſtifies us, ſhall condemn thee eternally,</hi> Ibid. p. 33.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>If this was a man of God, who may we account a man of—. The memorable Works of this <hi>Edw. Burroughs</hi> may ſerve as Memorials to all men, to dread <hi>the Spirit and Principles of the Quakers,</hi> theſe inſtances being ſuch Monuments of their folly and madneſs: He ſaith, <hi>That impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and non-imputation, and to talk of a perſon juſtified and to be juſtified, is the language of</hi> Egypt, <hi>and is condemn'd to the lake of Perdition by the Light.</hi> But what kind of Light ſhould this be, that ſhould thus fatally doom ſuch a queſtion? and brand the perſon asking it for a <hi>Sorcerer?</hi> He ſaith, <hi>He owns no other Righteouſneſs but what is wrought by Chriſt;</hi> But not one word, <hi>whether this Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs is wrought without us, or within us, or both,</hi> which is the thing the queſtion aims at. If the Queriſt was, or if any perſon elſe be ignorant here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, ſo they may remain, for any thing that <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughs</hi> hath here contributed towards their infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.</p>
               <p n="16">(16. <hi>Q.</hi>) Whether Chriſt be in the Saints in reſpect of that Nature wherein he ſuffer'd at <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Here thou enemy of Chriſt wouldſt know how the Saints enjoy Chriſt; the Scripture is fulfil'd on thee the light ſhines in darkneſs, and the darkneſs comprehends it not; when thou comes to own thy
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:55411:23"/> Condemnation the light in thy Conſcience, then thou wilt know that Nature that Chriſt ſuffer'd in: But now thou art in the nature that</hi> Judas <hi>was in that betray'd him &amp; that they were in that crucified him,</hi> Ibid. p. 33.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Is there in this reply one word to the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion? could he not have anſwerd <hi>yea</hi> or <hi>nay,</hi> elſe where he grants that he who was ſlain upon the Croſs is the very Chriſt of God, <hi>and that the very Chriſt of God was in him,</hi> Ibid. p. 149. From whence we may infer, That the light within was crucified at <hi>Jeruſalem:</hi> Muſt this paſs for an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible dictate? ſurely not with any who are not under the influence of the <hi>Quakers</hi> deluſions. But wherefore did <hi>Burroughs</hi> remain under ſuch a Paroxiſm of fury, was it not becauſe each queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on did ſtrike too cloſely at your vile Opinions?</p>
               <p n="17">(17 <hi>Q.</hi>) How and in what manner Chriſt, who in reſpect of his Divine Nature, is in all places, may be ſaid to be in a Saint, and not in a Reprobate?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What haſt thou to do to quere after the Divine Nature, who art the natural man, who knows nothing of God, but what thou knoweſt naturally as a bruit beaſt: The manner of Chriſts Divine Nature is bid from thy eyes; with that eye thou ſhouldſt ſee, with that thou art blind: And the manner of his being in the Saints thou knowſt not, who art a Reprobate, and ſhalt find him to thy eternal condemnation,</hi> Ibid. p. 33, 34.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>It is a lamentable thing, that a man for asking, How and in what reſpect Chriſt may be ſaid to be in a Chriſtian? muſt be put off with ſuch a taunting reply as this, <hi>What haſt thou to do to quere, thou knowſt nothing but as a bruit beaſt, thou Reprobate.</hi> Is this to inſtruct with meekneſs and fear? we ſee, that if we do not believe your
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:55411:23"/> ſayings without farther enquiry what will come on't, namely, to be curs'd and damn'd eternally. 'Twas pity this queſtion did not fall into the hands of a more judicious perſon then <hi>Edw. Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughs,</hi> who neither treats the Queriſt, nor his queſtion, like a Chriſtian, or a ſober man.</p>
               <p>(18 Q) Whether doth Chriſt now in theſe days aſſume, or take upon him, the form of a Servant, &amp; the ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> that is our fleſh, and whether doth not this aſſumption cauſe ſuch a perfection of the Godhead and the Manhood, as that both of them together are united into one Perſon.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>O thou dark Beaſt and Conjurer, quering with thy conjured words, that which thou knowſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of, and is out of thy reach and comprehenſion: Thou Blaſphemer, doſt thou limit Chriſt to dayes, in taking upon him the form of a Servant, and the ſeed of</hi> Abraham; <hi>Is not he the ſame now as ever he was? for the union of the Godhead with the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, as thou calls it: Let thy mouth be ſtopt, for with thee God nor none of his Children hath any uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; God hath put an utter enmity betwixt thy ſeed, thou Serpent, and the ſeed of the woman. And the perfect union with Chriſt we witneſs, therefore are we ſeparate from thee and thy Generation,</hi> Ibid. p. 34.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>I perceive he that ſate him on, carried him through; otherwiſe, by this time, we might reaſonably conclude he ſhould have been drawn dry of his virulent and undecent expreſſions: Be the queſtion what it will, he was at no loſs for words to ſtigmatize and vilifie the Queriſt; yet was at a real and marvellous loſs to give a direct anſwer to the purpoſe, almoſt all the queſtions hath a fair, or rather (if you will) a foul go-by:
<gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:55411:24"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:55411:24"/>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:55411:25"/> Let me ſeriouſly ask thee, whether thou doſt indeed believe that <hi>Edw. Burroughs was in the meekneſs, plainneſs and ſimplicity?</hi> when he did repreſent the perſon that asked, whether Chriſt doth now take upon him the form of a Servant, <hi>to be a dark Beaſt and Conjurer?</hi> Doſt thou believe that Chriſt now in theſe dayes takes on him the form of a Servant? our Fleſh, as once he did? Do not reply in equivocal terms, but ſpeak honeſtly and plainly to the queſtion; we ask you not, what you witneſs, we will not be determined by your vain boaſts, or deluded fancies.</p>
               <p n="19">(19. <hi>Q.</hi>) Whether Chriſt is now converſant with men upon Earth, ſince his Aſcenſion, as he was before, and in thoſe times wherein the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles lived?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thy quere bewrayes thee, thy language is the language of</hi> Egypt; <hi>thou makeſt it clearly mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, thou knowſt not Chriſt in any meaſure, where the firſt principle of truth is made manifeſt; it is the ſame that ever was: Thou askeſt whether Chriſt be not now converſant upon Earth amongſt men, ſince his Aſcenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as he was in the Apoſtles times; doſt thou know what thou askeſt? Did not Chriſt appear to his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles ſince his aſcenſion in the moſt glorious manner that ever was? and is he not the ſame now as he was then? what? wouldſt thou make of Chriſt, thou</hi> dark ſottiſh beaſt, <hi>ſuch a one as thy ſelf,</hi> Ibid. p. 34.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>This man took a liberty to ſay any thing, but what was to the purpoſe; 'tis amazing to think that a perſon under his Character, being under no ſurprize or provocation, ſhould delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately write ſuch groſs Errors and Untruths, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with ſuch a heap of ſcurrilous and filthy
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:55411:25"/> Railings, and cauſe theſe to be printed for the view of future Generations. <hi>Burroughs</hi> asks, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Chriſt did not appear to the Apoſtles ſince his Aſcenſion? <hi>who denies he did:</hi> But what is this to the queſtion, whether <hi>Chriſt be now conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant with men upon Earth ſince his Aſcenſion, as he was before?</hi> To this the Quaker Replies, What would thou make of Chriſt, <hi>thou dark ſottiſh beaſt?</hi> But whether this be a ſolution of the queſtion, I ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit it to others.</p>
               <p n="20">(20. <hi>Q.</hi>) Whether Chriſt did not dwell amongſt the Saints after another manner, and more viſible then now he dwells in them?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Here thou ſhews thy ignorance, and for thy word</hi> viſible <hi>he is not, nor never viſible to thee, nor thy Generation; for thoſe that did profeſs the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures as thou, and thy Generation doth, crucified him: Thou Blaſphemer, where ſaith the Scripture that Chriſt would dwell after another manner in his Saints?</hi> Ibid. p. 34.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>In this Anſwer, the Quaker denies that Chriſt was ever <hi>viſible</hi> to wicked men (ſuch as he eſteems the Queriſt to be) and conſequently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies <hi>that perſon call'd in the Scriptures by this name, who convers'd here in the World, and ſuffer'd death openly and viſibly at</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>to be the Chriſt;</hi> for that Chriſt was viſible to wicked men: But this bold man ſaith, <hi>Chriſt was never viſible</hi> to ſuch as the Queriſt is: Are not theſe things <hi>juſtly offenſive to Chriſtian ears?</hi> 'Tis too evident in your acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgments of Jeſus Chriſt, you do but abuſe your Readers, in owning that in words which in truth you really deny, and do ſteal away the truth from the leſs wary reader or hearer, even then when in
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:55411:26"/> words you ſeem to confeſs it. It is blaſphemy (ſaith <hi>Edw. Burroughs</hi>) To ſay Chriſt dwells in another manner in the Saints, then once he did amongſt them; which is as much as to ſay, <hi>Chriſt is not a perſon without them.</hi> Did <hi>Edw. Burroughs believe</hi> that theſe replies of his were proper an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers to the queſtions.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bleſſed be the Lord that hath diſcovered thee; ſo thy queries are anſwer'd in the eternal life and light of God, and Judgment is given upon thee and them, which thou ſhalt eternally witneſs: Thy queries are anſwer'd lovingly and plainly, and in the Scripture language and terms, and with the eternal light and life of God ſet thee in thy own place, which thou ſhalt eternally witneſs,</hi> Ibid. p. 34.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>What horrid blaſphemy, arrogance, and wilful lying, are theſe few concluding words guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of? to ſay theſe queries are anſwer'd in <hi>the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life and light of God,</hi> is a moſt blaſphemous <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituling the Divine Majeſty to all</hi> Edw. Burroughs <hi>his multiplyed Railings, Lies, and Impertinencies;</hi> Could the Devil himſelf have been more vile? and was it not prodigious arrogancy in this man to take upon him <hi>to determine a mans endleſs condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</hi> Is it not alſo a moſt odious lye, to ſay theſe queries are anſwer'd <hi>lovingly and plainly, in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture language and terms?</hi> Is railing, curſing, and damning a perſon, <hi>loving and plain anſwers?</hi> Is ſot and ſottiſh Beaſt, &amp;c. <hi>Scripture language and terms?</hi> The Lord in mercy deliver us from ſuch Prophets, who are juſtly worthy of the abhorrence of all men.</p>
               <p>Thus I have given you ſome account of the memorable works <hi>(of this eminent Quaker)</hi> printed 1672. with the Epiſtles of <hi>Ellis Hooks, Joſiah Coale,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:55411:26"/> George Whitehead, Francis Howgill,</hi> and <hi>George Fox,</hi> that the Ages to come may ſee what monſters this Age produced: <hi>O my Soul come not thou into their Secrets, unto their Aſſembly,</hi> Gen. 49.6. I preſume by this time thou maiſt be ſatisfied, that I have not wrong'd you in the Dialogue, but did therein re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent you, and your manner of ſpeaking, in more favourable terms then you ſee I could, or might have done, what farther have you to object?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>We ſay they are lyes and ſlanders, and thou art a moſt irreligious miſcreant.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Several of you <hi>(that were moved thus to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs your minds)</hi> being asked, whether you had read the Dialogue? <hi>anſwer'd No;</hi> How then do you know they are all lyes? Is it not a moſt diſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious thing to paſs ſentence on you know not what? I ſee 'tis as eaſie to waſh the <hi>Blackmoor</hi> white, as 'tis to reclaim you from this accuſtomed evil. Thoſe of you who have read the Dialogue, may know (if you will) that I have not onely quoted your Books, but have done it truly and honeſtly; can this then be of any Service to you, when any perſon that examines the quotations, may ſee your error: As for that term miſcreant, <hi>George White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head</hi> is pleas'd to impoſe upon me; I think it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of any farther notice then this, that for want of argument, he takes up dirt, which was no wayes becoming him, having told us in print, <hi>That he never found any man convinced by ill lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, Divinity of Chriſt,</hi> p. 89. What more haſt thou to ſay?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thou ſayſt, We hold the Soul to be God, whereas we diſtinguiſh between the Power that ſaves, and that which is ſaved,</hi> G. W. Dip. Pl. p. 15.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:55411:27"/>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Did I not cite your metropolitan <hi>G. Fox?</hi> direct you to his Book and Page, where you may read theſe words, <hi>That the Soul is part of Gods Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, without beginning; and infinite;</hi> Dareſt thou ſay, I have not quoted him truly? But ſaith <hi>George Whitehead,</hi> We diſtinguiſh between the Soul and its Saviour; So doth <hi>G. Fox</hi> ſeem to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh, When he calls God the Biſhop of the Soul, notwithſtanding which, he ſaith, The Soul is a part of Gods Being; If then there be any thing in his diſtinction, 'tis onely this, <hi>That one part of God is Biſhop over another. George White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head</hi> alſo pretends to diſtinguiſh between Chriſt, and his light or gift, <hi>Apolog.</hi> 35. And yet in his <hi>Dip. Pl. p.</hi> 13. ſaith, <hi>The life is the light of men, and this life and light is divine and increated;</hi> ſo that the meaning of his diſtinction muſt be, <hi>That Chriſt is not divine and increated, but his Light is:</hi> If both be increated, what ſignifies his diſtinction? <hi>James Naylor</hi> likewiſe diſtinguiſheth between <hi>the light and the ſeed within;</hi> and yet tells us, <hi>The light is Chriſt, and the ſeed is Chriſt;</hi> ſo that your di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhing is but a colluſion to baffle and amuſe ſimple and ignorant people: Hence, as one of your own Friends hath ſaid of you, we find but too true; though your years have been but few, yet you have been exceeding expert in learning the ſubtilties <hi>(that is, the equivocations)</hi> of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts. Who of you ever writ againſt this poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>George Fox</hi> concerning the Soul? Or which of you dare give it under your hands, That herein your <hi>Superintendent was decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:55411:27"/>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whereas thou haſt ſaid, we deny the Perſon of Chriſt, herein thou art a lyar; the perſon of Chriſt we own and witneſs.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>But do you acknowledge him to be a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct perſon without you?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jeſus Chriſt a Perſon without us, is not Scripture language, but the Anthropomorphites and Muggletonians,</hi> Whitehead, Dip. Pl. p. 13.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>If Jeſus Chriſt be not a Perſon diſtinct from you, who or what is Jeſus Chriſt?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>'Tis God himſelf;</hi> if God be the Light, and that Light be Chriſt, then God is Chriſt, <hi>Penns Innocency with open face,</hi> p. 8. <hi>Again, 'tis the light in us,</hi> we own no other Redeemer but that Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, the Son of God, who died at <hi>Jeruſalem, who is the light in us, Naylor</hi> and <hi>Hubborthorns</hi> anſwer to the <hi>Phanatique Hiſtory,</hi> p. 13.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>You ſay you own the Perſon of Chriſt, is the light in you a perſon? and is it the very Son of God? and did it indeed die at <hi>Jeruſalem?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>We ſay, He that was ſlain upon the Croſs is the very Chriſt of God, and the very Chriſt of God is in us,</hi> Burroughs Works, <hi>p.</hi> 9. 149.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>If God be Chriſt, as <hi>Penn ſaith;</hi> or if the Light within you be the Chriſt, as <hi>Naylor</hi> and <hi>Hub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berthorne affirm?</hi> Is it proper or ſafe to ſay, God was ſlain, or that the Light in you was crucified?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ye have condemn'd and kill'd the Juſt,</hi> James 5. 5, 6. <hi>that is, Chriſt Jeſus in their hearts, him they crucified,</hi> G. Keith. <hi>Immediat. Revelation,</hi> p. 77.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Is Chriſt really and indeed crucified in the hearts of men onely.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>As Chriſt is and lives in himſelf, he cannot
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:55411:28"/> be crucified, but his appearance may,</hi> Keith. Ibid.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>You diſtinguiſh between <hi>Chriſt, and his appearance;</hi> and ſay, He himſelf cannot, but his appearance may be crucified; Is not this as much as to ſay, His appearance is but a Creature? But how will this agree with the Dictates of others of your Miniſtry, who ſay, The Light within <hi>is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine and increated:</hi> I perceive if we examine you diſtinct, your tales will not agree. And when <hi>G. Keith.</hi> ſaith, Ye kill'd the Juſt, that is <hi>Chriſt Jeſus:</hi> Muſt we believe that this Juſt is not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed Chriſt Jeſus, but onely his appearance; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently when the Scripture ſaith, Chriſt was crucified, we muſt not underſtand it was Chriſt himſelf, <hi>but onely an Image, appearance, or ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation of him was crucified,</hi> and all this too within our Hearts. But is this one of thoſe things which you ſay are <hi>neceſſary to be reveal'd to you, which are not to be found in the Scriptures, no not ſo much as by conſequence,</hi> Ibid. p. 3, 4.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now thy perverſe and cavilling mind diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covers it ſelf.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Do you believe that Chriſt is now in Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon at the right hand of God?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>He is at the right hand of God, but I cannot believe he hath a perſonal being at the right hand of God without all men,</hi> G. Whitehead, <hi>Chriſt aſcended,</hi> p. 18. <hi>Chriſt in Perſon remote in a body of fleſh, and not in men is not Scripture, but added,</hi> Ibid. p. 69.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>What then do you intend by the right hand of God, and of Chriſts being there?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chriſt, nor Gods right hand, is not to be li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited to a remoteneſs from the Saints,</hi> Ibid. p. 18. <hi>What do you mean by Gods right hand, and Chriſts
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:55411:28"/> being at Gods right hand,</hi> that would ſeem to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine them out of all men, Ibid. p. 20, 21.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Is Chriſt no otherwiſe at Gods right hand, then as he is in you?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>'Tis a falſe and lying Imagination to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine either Chriſt or God, and his right hand, to be ſo remote as not to dwell in any man,</hi> Whitehead, Ibid. p. 69.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Is the heavens, that muſt retain him till the times of the reſtitution of all things, onely the hearts of men?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I have told thee plainly, that neither Chriſt, nor Gods right hand are ſo remote, as not to dwell in men, and that Chriſt hath not a perſonal being at Gods right hand.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Doth not the Scripture ſay, That the ſame Jeſus that went away, ſhall in like manner come again? <hi>Acts</hi> 1.10, 11.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I deny he ſhall ccome viſibly; and though it be ſaid in like manner, yet every like is not the ſame,</hi> Whitehead, Ibid. p. 22.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Is not this a plain denial of the ſecond perſonal coming of Chriſt?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>They are like to be deceived, who are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting that Chriſts ſecond coming will be</hi> a perſonal coming; <hi>which word</hi> perſon <hi>you add to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, not minding the penalty,</hi> Revel. 22. G. White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, <hi>Ibid. p.</hi> 23.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>'Tis ſaid, When he comes, that every eye ſhall ſee him, they that peirced him, &amp;c.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>To ſay, They that pierced</hi> that Body, <hi>ſhall ſee</hi> that Body, <hi>are not Scripture words, but added; you do herein ſhew your carnal expectations, mean thoughts, unſcriptural conceptions of Chriſt; where
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:55411:29"/> doth the Scripture ſay, That Chriſt ſhall come in Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon?</hi> G. Whitehead, <hi>Ibid. p.</hi> 21, 22.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>In one breath you confeſs, That <hi>Chriſt roſe with the ſame Body that was crucified,</hi> and that he aſcended into Glory, <hi>Ibid. p.</hi> 17. And in another you ſpeak thus, <hi>To ſay Chriſt aſcended with the ſame body which roſe from the dead, and is at Gods right hand with that body; and that he hath a perſonal be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at Gods right hand you cannot believe,</hi> Ibid. p. 17, 18. Who is able to reconcile theſe Contradictions? In which of your ſayings ſhall we believe you, 'tis evident, you did but diſſemble in the firſt, that you might entrap and deceive your unwary Reader.</p>
               <p>But if Chriſt's <hi>ſecond coming</hi> will not be <hi>perſonal,</hi> pray tell us what you mean by his ſecond coming?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Be ſober, and hope to the end, for the grace that ſhall be brought to you at the Revelation of Jeſus Chriſt, when he ſhall appear</hi> in you <hi>glorified, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was crucified in weakneſs, but now is raiſed in Power,</hi> G. Keith. Im. Re. p. 77.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>If this be the ſecond appearance and coming of Chriſt, as in your Book 'tis called, pray what is the firſt coming?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Till that time the day dawn, and the day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtar ariſe in our hearts; he directs them to a light that ſhineth in a dark place, which is</hi> the ſame Jeſus Chriſt in his firſt appearance, <hi>as the ſeed ſown, a ſeed of light, but not come forth to the perfect day; this is the moſt ſure and firm word of Propheſie, whereunto we do well to take heed for the time,</hi> Keith. Ibid.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Then Chriſt's coming in the form of a Servant to ſuffer and die, was no coming at all; for his <hi>firſt appearance, you ſay, is the light that ſhineth in a dark place;</hi> and the ſecond is, when he <hi>(that
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:55411:29"/> is in his appearance)</hi> ſhall in you be glorified, ſo that <hi>a perſonal coming</hi> in any reſpect is manifeſtly denied by you. And ſince you deny Chriſt in his perſonal Being and Exiſtence, pray tell me, Hath he no Body?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yea, the Church is his Body,</hi> Edw. Burroughs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>What do you mean by the Church, is it Perſons, or onely a Seed, or Spirit in Men?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>'Tis the Seed.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Where is ſuch a Seed call'd the Body of Chriſt, do you believe Chriſt hath no other Body but this?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is not our wonted courſe to ſay Chriſt hath no Body but his Church, but we ſay the Church is his Body,</hi> Burroughs Works, p. 150.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Why do you not ſpeak directly, Hath Chriſt no other Body but his Church?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>This is an enſnaring queſtion, I ſhall not anſwer to ſatisfie thee, nor may I feed thy Serpents Wiſdom,</hi> Burroughs, Ibid.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>What ſnare can be in this queſtion, if you do indeed believe that Chriſt hath another Body.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>To ſay Chriſt hath two Bodies,</hi> one out of the ſight of the Saints; <hi>there is ſo much wickedneſs and ignorance in the Broachers of ſuch a particular, that it needs no anſwer,</hi> Burroughs, Ibid. 151, 152.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Then <hi>Burroughs</hi> and <hi>G. Whitehead</hi> both agree in denying Chriſt to have a Body diſtinct from his Church.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Them that accuſe us for ſaying Chriſt hath but</hi> one Body, <hi>ſhould produce Scripture that ſaith he</hi> hath two; <hi>and where doth the Scripture ſay, That Chriſts glorified Body in heaven is of a humane nature,</hi> G. Whiteheads Apolog. p. 33.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:55411:30"/>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>'Tis apparent then, you acknowledge no other Chriſt but the light in you; this, and this only is the very perſon of Chriſt in your judgment.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>They who deny Chriſt to be the light in every man are Antichriſts,</hi> Burroughs, Ibid. p. 127.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>But is the very Perſon of Chriſt in every man?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Goſpel is preached in every Creature under heaven,</hi> Whitehead, <hi>Chriſt aſcended,</hi> p. 63.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>I know by Goſpel you mean Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, but is Chriſt himſelf preach'd in <hi>Devils, Beaſts, Trees,</hi> and in every <hi>flagitious and wicked perſon;</hi> yea, is Chriſt himſelf in every <hi>Reprobate?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>When we ſay</hi> Chriſt is in Reprobates, <hi>you muſt underſtand the</hi> light or gift of Chriſt; <hi>for we do not expreſs the light in every man to be Chriſt,</hi> George Whiteheads Apol. p. 35. <hi>'Tis not our Principle to</hi> ſay Chriſt is in every man; <hi>'tis falſhood to accuſe us with affirming, that Chriſt is in every man,</hi> White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, <hi>Chriſt aſcended,</hi> p. 66.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>What vile hypocriſie and deceit is this <hi>Whitehead</hi> guilty of, he himſelf ſaith, The Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures direct to the Rule, <hi>that is, the light within that gave them forth,</hi> Chriſt aſcended, p. 42. <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughs</hi> affirms, <hi>That they who deny Chriſt to be the light in every man are Antichriſts.</hi> But I would ask <hi>Whitehead,</hi> whether this light or gift <hi>be created or increated:</hi> If the former, then 'tis but <hi>a meer crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture:</hi> If the latter, as he affirms in his <hi>Dip. Pl. p.</hi> 13. <hi>To ſay the light within every man is a meer creature, is</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>contrary to plain Scripture,</hi> which ſaith, In him was life, and the life was the light of men; <hi>this life and light is divine and increated.</hi> Is <hi>White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head</hi> then to be believed in ſaying, 'Tis not your
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:55411:30"/> Principle to ſay Chriſt is in every man, whilſt he openly denies <hi>the light within to be a creature,</hi> and ſaith, <hi>'Tis divine and increated:</hi> This kind of ſaying and denying is ſo common with him, that I profeſs 'tis a very hard and difficult point with me to know when he ſpeaks as he thinks; from the whole, you ſee I had juſt reaſon to accuſe you for denying the perſon of Chriſt: But ſince you own the name <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and do make uſe of it, pray what doth it ſignifie?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chriſt ſignifies anointed.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>If God himſelf be Chriſt, <hi>as Penn ſaith,</hi> I would quere <hi>whether God himſelf was anointed:</hi> If you will dare to affirm this, then tell me by whom, with what, and to what end he was anointed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>This we ſay, that Chriſt as the Son of God before the world, before he took Fleſh,</hi> was the anointed of God, <hi>which anointing was ſpiritual, and ſpiritually received by the heavenly Birth, the anointed, the holy ſeed,</hi> Whitehead, Chriſt aſcended, p. 68.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>This is ſtill as much as to ſay, that <hi>God himſelf was anointed:</hi> If ſo, what was the unction, by whom powred upon him, and wherefore?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now thou obtrudes queſtions.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Will you not ſpeak intelligibly? Is it not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to underſtand who is the <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was <hi>anointed;</hi> what ſignifies your ſaying, The anointing was ſpiritual, and ſpiritually recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the heavenly birth, the holy ſeed? <hi>Is God himſelf a heavenly Birth, did he receive the anointing?</hi> pray be plain, and do not lurk in ambiguous terms, neither let us be put off with your blaſphemous abſurdities, but ſpeak home to the point.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alas for thee, theſe are myſteries thy dark mind cannot conceive or underſtand.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:55411:31"/>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Is it not your duty <hi>(who pretend to be under infallible teachings)</hi> to endeavour my information in ſuch important and weighty matters.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wilt thou deny that the Son of God, before the world, before he took fleſh, was the anointed of God.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>I do not deny, but really believe the <hi>eternal Deity of the Son of God;</hi> yet I do deny, that the meer <hi>Godhead</hi> of the Son was the anointed Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our: And thou muſt prove, that the Son of God, <hi>meerly as God,</hi> is the Chriſt; for what thou haſt yet ſaid is no proof.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is not what I have ſaid ſufficient.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>In no wiſe; however thou mayſt take time to conſider on it, mean while let me ask thee, whether Chriſt was not Gods gift?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yea, he was ſo.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>To what end, and in what reſpect is he the gift of God?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>His Doctrine, Life, Miracles, Death and Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings to God, is the gift and expreſſion of Gods eternal love for the ſalvation of men,</hi> Penns Sand. Foun. p. 19.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Thou haſt affirmed, That <hi>God is Chriſt;</hi> if ſo, <hi>did God himſelf die, and ſuffer to God?</hi> and therein expreſs his love for the ſalvation of men; or if the <hi>Son of God the heavenly Birth, which was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the world, and before he took fleſh, as</hi> Whitehead <hi>talks,</hi> be only the anointed Saviour; was this ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply of it ſelf given to die, and <hi>ſuffer to God?</hi> or if the meer light within be the Chriſt, will you ſay, This was given to die and ſuffer to God, and therein to expreſs Gods eternal love for the ſalvation of men? who can underſtand theſe things? Are not ſuch dictates apparent indications of your diſtracted minds?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:55411:31"/>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>We ſay Chriſt is the gift of Gods eternal love for the ſalvation of men, and wilt thou deny this?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Though I do grant it, yet I ſee you will take a liberty to ſay that at one time, and in one place, which can never be reconciled with, your ſayings in another, and that you run your ſelves into ſuch <hi>a labyrinth of confuſion and contradiction,</hi> that all the light you have cannot extricate you out of, and conſequently that your pretences to <hi>infallibility</hi> is a meer lying deluſion: For you neither conſiſt with the truth, nor your ſelves; yet give me leave to ask you, whether one great end wherefore Chriſt was given, and came into the world, was not <hi>to ſeek and to ſave ſuch that were loſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yea, he came to ſeek and to ſave the loſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>But who, or what is this that was loſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>That which was loſt, is ſtill in mans heart, and there it muſt be ſought; for it remains ſtill in the houſe (that is) mans heart:</hi> This <hi>is the thing to be ſought for.</hi> This <hi>Chriſt came to ſeek and ſave, and all his Miniſters preach'd people to</hi> this; the loſt in man, <hi>that it might be found;</hi> a loſt God, a loſt Chriſt, <hi>this was the ſum and ſubſtance of their Doctrine,</hi> G. Keith. Im. Re. p. 75, 76.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Bluſh O Heavens, and be aſtoniſh'd O Earth, was ever ſuch a thing as this heard of before? that Jeſus Chriſt came to ſeek and ſave <hi>a loſt God, a loſt Chriſt;</hi> was ever God and Chriſt in a loſt conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? If you had ſaid, That Jeſus Chriſt came to ſeek and ſave Sinners who were in a loſt condition, and to ſtir them up to ſeek after God, whom they had loſt, you had ſpoken ſafely: But to ſay <hi>this,</hi> Chriſt came to ſeek and ſave, and all his Miniſters preach'd people to <hi>this,</hi> the loſt in man, <hi>a loſt God, a loſt
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:55411:32"/> Chriſt;</hi> Is not capable of any conſtruction leſs then blaſphemy. To this agrees <hi>James Naylor,</hi> who ſaid, Chriſt came to <hi>redeem the ſeed within,</hi> which he of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten calls <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Is this another of thoſe things you ſay are neceſſary to be reveal'd to you, <hi>which are not to be found in Scripture, not ſo much as by conſequence;</hi> And are theſe your inſtances to prove you under <hi>immediate Inſpirations?</hi> If they be, they will prove no more, nor no leſs then this, that you are imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately <hi>inſpired and influenced by that grand Impoſtor the Devil.</hi> Pray what is your Opinion concerning Juſtification by that Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, which he in his own Perſon fulfil'd for us, wholly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out us.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Juſtification by the Righteouſneſs which Chriſt fulfil'd for us in his own Perſon, wholly without us; we boldly affirm it to be a doctrine of Devils, and an arm of the Sea of corruption, which doth now de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luge the World,</hi> William Penn, <hi>Apol. p.</hi> 148.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Is there no other Righteouſneſs by which the Saints are juſtified then what Chriſt works onely in them?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>Thou Beaſt, <hi>to whom the Plagues of God are due, and upon whom the wrath of God muſt be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh'd, who wouldſt have another Righteouſneſs then that which Chriſt works in the Saints,</hi> Edw. Burroughs Works, p. 32.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Is not this to diſclaim the Doctrine of Juſtification by an imputed Righteouſneſs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thou wrongſt us, and our Principle, for imputative Righteouſneſs, as truly conſider'd in the Scriptures, we do not diſclaim,</hi> G. Whitehead Apol. p. 37.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:55411:32"/>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>I have great reaſon to believe that <hi>G. W.</hi> diſſembles in theſe words, for in the <hi>ſame page</hi> he diſclaims them that deny <hi>the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt within for Juſtification;</hi> and alſo ſaith, That <hi>juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication by the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt without us</hi> is not Scripture language; who will believe his complaint of wrong, whilſt he ſo apparently confeſſeth the truth of what is objected againſt you, as will abundantly appear from what follows, what righteouſneſs is that upon the account of which we are juſtified?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Juſtification is not from the imputation of anothers Righteouſneſs, but from the actual per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming and keeping of Gods righteous Statutes,</hi> Pen. Sand. Found. p. 25.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Is it not written, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.19. By the Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of One, many were made righteous?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is a great abomination to ſay,</hi> God ſhould condemn and puniſh his innocent Son, <hi>that he having ſatisfied for our Sins, we might be juſtified by the imputation of his perfect Righteouſneſs.</hi> O why ſhould this horrible thing be contended for by Chriſtians? <hi>Penn, Ibid. p.</hi> 25. 30.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>How now Mr. <hi>Penn,</hi> is the Doctrine of Chriſt's Sufferings for Sinners to make ſatisfaction to Divine Juſtice an horrible thing, and an abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination to you; do you conſider what you ſay?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>This I do ſay, That the conſequences of ſuch a Doctrine is both irreligious and irrational,</hi> Pen. Ibid. p. 16.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>What then doth the Scripture intend, in ſaying Chriſt died for the ungodly, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. And he <hi>was made ſin for us,</hi> 2 Cor. 5. <hi>And on him was
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:55411:33"/> laid the Iniquities of us all,</hi> Iſa. 53.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I caution and warn men, by no means to entertain this principle</hi> (of Chriſt's dying to make ſatisfaction to Divine Juſtice) <hi>by whomſoever recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended,</hi> Pen. Ibid.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Be free and plain with me, How and in what reſpect is Chriſt ſaid to fulfil the Law, and to die for Sinners?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>He fulfil'd the Law</hi> onely as our pattern or example, <hi>Pen. Ibid. p.</hi> 26. <hi>Chriſt is ſo far from telling us of ſuch a way of being juſtified, as that be informs us the reaſon why he abode in his Fathers love, was his Obedience; he is ſo far from telling as of being juſtified by vertue of his Obedience imputed, that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs we keep the Commands, and obey for our ſelves;</hi> In all which Chriſt is but our example, <hi>Pen Ibid.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>But are men indeed juſtified by their own works?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Was not</hi> Abraham <hi>juſtified by works; n<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> muſt not conceive, as the dark imputations of the Age, that</hi> Abrahams perſonal offering <hi>was not a juſtifying Righteouſneſs,</hi> Pen. Ibid. p. 30.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Was not <hi>Abraham</hi> juſtified before he did perſonally offer up <hi>Iſaac?</hi> ye<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, doth not the Scripture intimate, that <hi>Abraham</hi> was not juſtified by works, ſee <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7. And do not you (Mr. <hi>Penn</hi>) elſewhere tell us, <hi>That ſuch are run into a narrow ſtrait, who venture to reconcile Merit and Grace. See your caveat againſt Popery.</hi> p. 12. <hi>where you alſo ſay, That Grace is a free gift, requiring nothing;</hi> and now ask, Was not <hi>Abraham</hi> juſtified by works, <hi>and that good works may be ſaid to procure, deſerve, or obtain,</hi>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:55411:33"/> Apolog. 198. Is this to write like an infalible Dictator? But do you really believe that <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi>'s <hi>offering perſonally</hi> was his juſtifying Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I do ſay</hi> Abraham <hi>had not the imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of anothers Righteouſneſs to him, his perſonal Obedience was the ground of that juſt imputation,</hi> Pen. Sand. Found. p. 30.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>If <hi>Abraham</hi> was juſtified by works, as you argue, why did the Apoſtle onely take notice of his offering up of <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and not of the whole courſe of his Obedience? If a man be juſtified by works before God, ſurely it cannot be by one <hi>ſingle action</hi> (ſuch as <hi>Abrahams</hi> offering was) but by a continued holy and innocent life. But is <hi>our perſonal Obedience</hi> the very ground and reaſon of Gods reckoning and accounting us righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I do maintain, that good works may be ſaid to procure, doſerve, or obtain; in which ſenſe, without good works, there is no acceptance with God;</hi> and <hi>Abrahams</hi> perſonal offering was the ground of that juſt imputation, <hi>Penn.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>God accepts not any where there is any failing, or who do not fulfil the Law, and anſwer every demand of Juſtice,</hi> Edw. Burroughs, <hi>ſupra.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Then the ground of our rejoycing, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance, is not in and from the Righteouſneſs of another, <hi>viz.</hi> of Chriſt imputed to us by Faith, but onely in a righteouſneſs inherent in us, and done by us.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Doctrine of rejoycing and acceptance from the works of another is utterly excluded,</hi> Pen. Sandy Found. p. 27.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:55411:34"/>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Doth not this render the undertakings <hi>of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> as <hi>a Mediatour and Surety,</hi> a meer fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy? If the ground of a mans rejoycing be in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, why doth the Apoſtle give it as the Character and property of a true Chriſtian, <hi>to rejoyce in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> Phil. 3. And what ſignifie thoſe words, <hi>Chriſt is made unto us Righteouſneſs; wherefore let him that glorieth, glory in the Lord,</hi> 1 Cor. 1.30, 31. And what did the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> intend, <hi>cap.</hi> 45, 24, 25. <hi>Surely ſhall one ſay, in the Lord have I Righteouſneſs, in the Lord ſhall all the ſeed of</hi> Iſrael <hi>be juſtified, and ſhall glory.</hi> Are we no farther concern'd in the Obedience and Sufferings of our Lord Jeſus with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out us, then onely as our example or pattern?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What more wouldſt thou have? I have told thee, That Chriſt fulfil'd the Law but onely as our example.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Do you not then notoriouſly <hi>equivocate and diſſemble,</hi> when you ſay, That <hi>Chriſts Birth, Blood, Offering, Death, Mediatourſhip, Covenant, his being Prieſt, Prophet, and King,</hi> is owned according to the Scriptures, and all the Propheſies of him, <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency with open face,</hi> p. 38. Is the owning of Chriſt onely as our example all that the Scriptures and Propheſies of him ſignifie; <hi>Can you imitate him in his Mediatourſhip? can you lay down your lives, and take them up again? Have you the ſame fulneſs of the Godhead in you he had,</hi> that you can follow him in the ſame Obedience? <hi>Can you execute the Office of Prieſt, Prophet, and King, in the ſame manner and perfection,</hi> which Chriſt did and doth? We know very well, how ever you palliate, you believe no ſuch thing that your words ſeem to import: For when you talk of <hi>Chriſts Birth, Blood, Death,</hi> &amp;c.
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:55411:34"/> you intend no more <hi>but the light in you,</hi> in its va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of manifeſtations; therefore if poſſibly thou canſt, anſwer directly what that Righteouſneſs is, which is reckoned or accounted to us for our Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Art thou of them, that imagine a Juſtification without Sanctification, who becauſe the Scriptures faith, God juſtifies the ungodly through Faith, they therefore conclude themſelves juſtified in their ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, by a fancy which they call Faith,</hi> Naylors Love to the Loſt, 50, 51. <hi>I farther tell thee, That Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication by an imputed Righteouſneſs is both irratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, irreligious, ridiculous and dangerous,</hi> Pen. Sand. Fo. p. 30, 31.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>I know of none that hold Juſtification of perſons <hi>in their ungodlineſs;</hi> this therefore is a wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſlander, and not at all to the queſtion: We plead not for a Righteouſneſs imputed, to overthrow a Righteouſneſs inherent, or the exerciſe of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an vertues; 'tis you would ſeparate and divide them, not we: The queſtion intends this, whether the perſon juſtified was not at that inſtant before he was juſtified guilty in himſelf?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Juſtification goes not before, but is conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quential to the mortifying of Luſts, and the ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the Soul: Again, impute or imputing ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies no more in Scripture, but to expreſs men really and perſonally to be what is imputed to them,</hi> Pen. Sand. Fo. p. 27, 29, 30.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Doth not this import, that a man muſt be formally juſt before he be juſtified, for nothing is imputed or reckoned to us (according to your reaſoning) but what is inherent in us: I would ask you, whether remiſſion of ſins be not one part of Juſtification?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:55411:35"/>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I ſuppoſe it may.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Can one be forgiven that is not guilty; it looks like a contradiction, to pardon one that is innocent, to forgive one that owes nothing; cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly he that is pardoned muſt be a Sinner, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.5. that is, ſuch that were ſo till juſtified, not ſuch that remain ſo being juſtified.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>God juſtifies the living, and not the dead, whilſt the Juſt being dead in treſpaſſes and ſins: There is no juſtification where the Juſt lives not, for by that which the Juſt lives, is that by which the creature is juſtified,</hi> Naylors Love to the loſt, 52. Printed 1656.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>To talk of the <hi>Juſt being dead in treſpaſſes and ſins,</hi> is no other then your abſurd blaſphemous and ridiculous canting. For <hi>by Juſt,</hi> we know you mean <hi>the ſeed of God</hi> in man, which ſometimes you call <hi>Chriſt, or his appearance, gift or meaſure:</hi> But is <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or his <hi>Seed</hi> or <hi>Power</hi> in man, <hi>dead in ſins and treſpaſſes?</hi> what unworthy and vile Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are you to ſuggeſt ſuch perillous conceits as theſe, and yet pretend to infallibility and perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; by what hath been ſaid, I am (and preſume others may be) fully ſatisfied what kind of Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation you hold: Pray let us underſtand your Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Sanctification, what it is:</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>'Tis Chriſt himſelf; hence we conclude, To ſay Sanctification is imperfect in this life, is as much as to ſay, Chriſt is imperfect; but Chriſt is perfect, therefore Sanctification is perfect: See then the error and wickedneſs of this principle, that Sanctification is imperfect,</hi> Edw. Burrough's Works 488.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>'Tis true, <hi>Jeſus Chriſt by his Spirit</hi> is the Author and Worker of Sanctification; but will it therefore follow, that the work of Sanctification
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:55411:35"/> in us is <hi>Chriſt himſelf,</hi> or that this work is now perfect in all its degrees.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>Jeſus Chriſt <hi>is both the ſeeds man, the ſeed, and alſo the fruit,</hi> G. Keith. Im. R. p. 77. <hi>The Law in the mind is</hi> the Spirit of God: <hi>To ſay the Law in the mind is imperfect, is error in the higheſt degree; this is an abominable corrupt principle of error, the new man is perfect peace, and perfect ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication,</hi> Burroughs, Ibid. 488.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>How wilt thou prove that <hi>Chriſt is both the Author, and the work, the ſeeds-man, and the ſeed, and fruit?</hi> That the Law in the mind is the <hi>Spirit it ſelf,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt himſelf;</hi> and that the new man is perfect ſanctification, that there remains not the leaſt ſin either for kind or degree in the perſon ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified; we will not be impoſed upon, therefore, if you can, demonſtrate this thing unto us.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>If the old man, the body of ſin, remain in ſanctified perſons, then none are ſanctified at all; and ſuch as have the body of ſin in them, have no part in the Kingdom of God,</hi> Edw. Burroughs, Ibid. 488.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Why then doth the Apoſtle exhort ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied perſons to put off the old man, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.5. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.12, 13.</p>
               <p>And how will you prove your ſelves to have any part in the Kingdom of God, ſince 'tis notorious, the body of ſin yet remains in the beſt of you, of which your <hi>intollerable pride, error, envy, malice, railing curſing, hypocriſie, and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful lying</hi> are ſufficient evidences.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>We deny the old man, we are in the meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, truth, and ſimplicity; therefore thou ſuggeſts nothing but thy own imaginations.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>You are (as we ſay) far from your Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:55411:36"/> who elſe will ſay ſo of you beſides your ſelves, your own Teſtimony is not ſufficient in this eaſe; eſpecially ſince your Writings, Converſe, and Practiſe <hi>gives the lye</hi> to this your pretence, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient inſtances hath in this Diſcourſe been ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted to prove you guilty; therefore your denial is an aggravation of your ſin and wickedneſs. But to the queſtion, doth Sanctification conſiſt in our conformity to the will of God or not?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now thou runs into the many words, thy fleſhly and imaginary diſtinctions.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>When wilt thou forbear theſe trifling Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinencies, Speak to the point.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I have told thee, That the Law in the mind</hi> is the Spirit of God, <hi>and that Chriſt is Sanctification, can I ſpeak more plain?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>If the Law in the mind be the <hi>Spirit it ſelf,</hi> and if Sanctification <hi>be Chriſt himſelf,</hi> what muſt we call obedience <hi>to Chriſt, his Law or Spirit?</hi> If our habitual and actual conformity to the divine Law or Rule be our holineſs, how can <hi>the Spirit it ſelf</hi> and <hi>Chriſt himſelf</hi> meerly be it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>We deny not, but declare, That all men ought to be obedient to the light,</hi> Chriſt <hi>in them.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>But may this obedience be call'd <hi>our holineſs?</hi> you ſeem to deny it, in ſaying <hi>Chriſt himſelf is San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification,</hi> and the <hi>Law in the mind</hi> is the <hi>Spirit of God:</hi> Doſt <hi>Chriſt obey himſelf, doth he repent and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve,</hi> and is his <hi>obeying himſelf in us</hi> our holineſs? If ſo, then whilſt you deny an imputed Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in a Scripture ſenſe, you maintain <hi>a righteouſneſs imputed in an enthuſiaſtical and ridiculous ſenſe.</hi> But if you will ſay, That obedience to the divine Rule is our holineſs, then you will contradict your ſelves. And to apply it to you, I would ask, How it
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:55411:36"/> is poſſible for you to prove your ſelves <hi>ſanctified perſons,</hi> that ſo wilfully and wickedly oppoſe <hi>the rule of duty:</hi> Did ever any holy man deliberately affirm, <hi>That is no command to me which is a command to another, neither did any of the Saints act by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand which was given to another; they every one obey'd his own command,</hi> Burroughs, Ibid. p. 47. Then that Law which forbids <hi>Idolatry, Adultery, Murder, Theft, and hearing falſe witneſs,</hi> &amp;c. is no Law to you, foraſmuch as it was given to others, and you ſay, We are not to act <hi>by the command which was to another;</hi> no wonder you pay ſo little; reſpect <hi>to Parents, Magiſtrates, Maſters,</hi> &amp;c. for that you will ſay was a command to others, therefore no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to you; ſo that neither the affirmative, nor the negative Precepts have any obligation upon you; for you have a peculiar diſpenſation, onely to obey your own command? Are you not, oh ye Quakers, aſhamed of this Doctrine?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>By order and authority given me by the Spirit of the living God, on the</hi> 31 day of the 10th moneth, 1655. about four a Clock in the morning, <hi>The word of the Lord came to me, ſaying, Write my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie with all the Inhabitants of the Earth Hence I do ſay, That to take up a command from the Letter, and ſay Chriſt commands it, that thus you are in the witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft,</hi> Edw. Burroughs works, p. 96. <hi>comp. with</hi> p. 105.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Is it witchcraft to ſtand in awe of Chriſt's commands, to reverence their authority, to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to our utmoſt an obſervance thereof? Did ever ſuch ungodly and irreverent Speeches drop from the mouth or pen of any truly Chriſtian man? And is it not <hi>impiouſly horrid,</hi> to make <hi>God himſelf to patronize ſuch blaſphemies;</hi> why do you counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:55411:37"/> ſuch Novices? Are you not yet aſhamed of thoſe Teſtimonies you have given to this moſt profane Scribler? And whereas you ſay, That no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing <hi>is a command to me which is a command to another;</hi> will you ſtand by it, that nothing is a duty to me but what I am immediately mov'd unto by the power within me:</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>'Tis an error to ſay, we are not to wait for an inward call, motion, impulſe, or inſpiration; to preach, pray, or to give thanks,</hi> ſo <hi>as to forbear till it be given,</hi> G. Keith. Im. Rev. Preface.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Am I not then ſinleſs, if Lomit the doing of any thing that may be good in it ſelf, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded in the Scriptures, if I be not immediately moved thereunto?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is it of good report,</hi> for unregenerate and uninſpired men to pray, <hi>Pen.</hi> Apol. p. 111. <hi>Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual obedience is not that wherein men and women read the Scriptures, and from that ſet themſelves on work, and ſo make an imitation of obedience,</hi> Naylors Love to the loſt, p. 27.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>People cry out of their beſt duties, as having ſin in them, had they not better let them alone: All theſe holy duties, as they call them, muſt down; had they not better let them alone, and ſee the ſalvation of God, and come to the gift,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Theſe laſt words, <hi>One of our Miniſtry was moved to declare very lately in a publick meeting in</hi> London. But is not this to teach men to be <hi>irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious and profane;</hi> no marvel <hi>Nicholas Lucas</hi> ſaid, We may <hi>burn the Bible,</hi> and ſerve God as well without it: But the queſtion returns upon you, whether this be not to lay all our neglects of doing that which is meet; yea, ought to be done, upon
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:55411:37"/> 
                  <hi>the power or ſpirit,</hi> for not immediately moving us thereunto? And what is your meaning, when you ſay <hi>theſe holy duties muſt down,</hi> and we had better let them alone, as having ſin in them: Is it not this? <hi>That there is no duty incumbent upon imperfect crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures?</hi> and that none muſt be perform'd, <hi>except it be perfect in the matter, manner, principle, and end:</hi> If ſo, are not all men diſcharg'd by you, from ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging the Soveraignty of God in thoſe Laws he hath given unto them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>You are not dead with Chriſt, who are yet ſubject unto Ordinances,</hi> Burroughs p. 105. <hi>Your Obedience is but the conformity in your own wills to that which was the will of God to another,</hi> Ibid.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>The Spirit of God in the Scriptures aſſures us, that they who are ſubject to, and keep the Commandments of God, are the Children of God, and they who do not are lyars, <hi>ſee the firſt Epiſtle of Joh.</hi> 2, 3, 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 5.2, 3. Yet this wicked man ſaith, That they who are ſubject to Ordinances are not dead with Chriſt, if you flee for refuge to <hi>Col.</hi> 2.20. It will not relieve you, for it is no ways applicable to the perſons to whom <hi>Edw. Burroughs</hi> did write; nor is his Speech limited to Jewiſh Ordinances (now aboliſhed) <hi>but was more general, reſpecting the Ordinances of Chriſt ſtill in force and being;</hi> and will you ſay theſe are not to be owned nor ſubjected unto, but onely ſo far as we are immediately moved and prompted by the power within.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>To go without the movings of the Spirit in your own wills, God hates, and his wrath is upon, if the movings of the Spirit do not carry forth to act them, they are accurſed of God. And all who go before the movings of it to carry forth, All their Prayers, Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:55411:38"/> and Ordinances I deny, and declare againſt, by the eternal Spirit of God, that they are odious, and abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination unto God,</hi> whether they be done in private, or in the Church, <hi>Edw. Burroughs</hi> Works, p. 47, 48.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Then we are really acquitted from any fault in omitting to do that which is good, and all the blame why it is not done, <hi>muſt be laid upon the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit:</hi> But is not this horrid? will this plea be of any ſervice to us (think you) in the day of acconut to ſay <hi>Lord, though I knew ſuch a thing ought to have been done, and ſuch an evil omitted; and that thou in the holy Scriptures did command the one, and forbid the other, yet that was nothing to me, I had no imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate motion or impulſe to do that, or forbear this.</hi> But what if one be moved to do thoſe things which are not commanded in the Scriptures, muſt that moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be followed?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>We affirm, That a great many particular things, both by</hi> way of precept, prohibition, permiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, approbation and counſel from the Lord, <hi>are both reveal'd, and neceſſary to be reveal'd to us, which are not</hi> eſſentials of the Chriſtian Religion, nor prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of the Doctrine of Chriſt, <hi>but things relating to our converſation in the world, and walking with God, with faith and comfort, according to his will, with the knowledg of which we are to be fill'd with in all things.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For there is a neceſſity for thoſe</hi> under the New Covenant diſpenſation <hi>of living in, and walking after the Spirit, to have things reveal'd to them from the Lord,</hi> which are not to be found in the Scriptures particularly, not ſo much as by conſequence, G. K. Im. Rev. p. 3. 4.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>If I may be ſo bold as to ask you, what are ſome of thoſe things which by way of <hi>precept or counſel from the Lord,</hi> which, you ſay, are neceſſary
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:55411:38"/> to be reveal'd to you, which yet <hi>are not to be found in the Scriptures, not ſo much as by conſequence:</hi> And how are you aſſured you have them from the Lord? and what evidence <hi>(more then your own pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences)</hi> can you give thereof to other men? Is <hi>your Friends,</hi> being moved to <hi>go naked,</hi> both <hi>men and women, openly in the Streets</hi> one of thoſe things? And is the caſting off <hi>the duties of Relations</hi> each to other, yea <hi>the relation itſelf,</hi> another? As I knew one of your Friends was moved to ramble about the Countrey, and neglect her Family at home; and once when ſhe return'd, it was upon her heart to ſignifie to her Husband <hi>(an honeſt, ſober, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious man, but no Quaker). That if he were free, he might take him another woman:</hi> I confeſs theſe things are not to be found in the Scriptures, not ſo much as by conſequence: Do you call this a living in, and walking after the Spirit? Is it not rather a following the conduct of the Prince of the power of the air? Again, what if one of you be moved to door ſpeak any thing which others of you are not ſatisfied in, muſt they obey that motion?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>That ſingle perſon muſt deny his motion, wherein it differs from the judgment of the Body</hi> (that is to ſay, the Court) <hi>which hath a true ſenſe, feeling, and underſtanding of motions, viſions, revelations and doctrines;</hi> therefore 'tis ſafeſt to make her the touchſtone in all things relating unto God, <hi>Spir of the Hat,</hi> p. 21.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Is not this as much as to ſay, that the power or ſpirit in and with the body is the only <hi>infallible and unerring rule,</hi> and not the power or meaſure (as you ſometimes call it) in any individual perſon? are you now after all your clamours about the ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency of the light or power in every man to be
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:55411:39"/> the rule, come <hi>to ſet up the light and ſpirit in the body above it?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Either there is ſuch a thing as a Chriſtian-ſociety, ſometimes call'd a viſible body, or there is not:</hi> If there be, <hi>then this Church either hath power or not;</hi> if no power, then no Church: <hi>If a Body or Church, then there muſt be a power within it ſelf to determine,</hi> Penns Spirit of Alexander, p. 9.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>For Chriſtians to plead this, who own the Scriptures for their rule, and not the meer light within, the argument may ſafely be allowed: But for you who tell us, <hi>That is no command to me which is a command to another, and every one muſt act from their own command,</hi> and the light in every man is his only unerring rule: I ſee not how you can urge this, and yet conſiſt with your ſelves. But in caſe one ſhould forbear what the Body would have done, or do what they forbid, what then?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quak.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>We abhor, renounce, and rebuke with ſeverity that rude imagination of the Hat on in publick Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er: In this caſe the Body may admoniſh, and if the Party remain tenacious, diſown him as a Diſputer about needleſs queſtions, and one that is gone out of the compleat union of the Body, and exerciſed by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Spirit,</hi> Penns Spirit of Alex. p. 4. 9.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Though others may, yet you cannot <hi>(if you will agree with your ſelves)</hi> ſtand by this: For will you ſay, What a man doth without an inward mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is <hi>accurſed,</hi> and yet will you diſown that man for not doing what he is not moved unto; will you ſay, <hi>There continually attends you that ſpirit that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately informs you of your words, thoughts, and deeds, and gives you true directions what to do, and what to leave undone,</hi> Penns Apol. p. 138. And now
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:55411:39"/> talk of a Body that hath power in it ſelf to determine, do you not herein render your ſelves juſtly ridiculous and contemptible in oppoſing that in others which yet you contend for amongſt your ſelves? And do you think this is the way to gain credit with any, whilſt you play faſt and looſe, affirm and deny at pleaſure? how can you impoſe that on another as his duty, <hi>which the light in him diſcovers not ſo to be?</hi> And how dare you deny ſuch, and call them <hi>unruly Beaſts,</hi> and Rant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſpirits, who meerly for the want of an inward motion forbear ſuch a practice? How you can do this, <hi>(your opinion that the light within is the only rule being conſidered)</hi> I cannot underſtand; If you will ſay that there is a known rule, and ſtandard to walk by, and this is not the meer light in every man, but another thing, to which that light muſt yield, and alſo tell us what that rule is, <hi>whether the Scriptures, or, the Power in the body.</hi> If you ſay either of theſe, you deny your firſt principle: If you affirm the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter onely, then you do but run from one extream to another, yea hopp out of the Frying-pan into the fire; <hi>If to take up a Command from the Scriptures, be (by you) accounted witchcraft?</hi> pray, what ſhall we call a taking up a command from the Body?</p>
               <p>But ſince you ſeem to be ſo zealous for the Miniſtry, will you be pleaſed to acquaint us what is the true Miniſtery?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>In the new Covenant, God is the teacher of his people himſelf Immediatly by his Immediate Spirit, pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and unction within,</hi> G. <hi>Whit. Chriſt aſcend.</hi> 64.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>If ſo; wherefore were <hi>Apoſtles, Prophets, Evangeliſts, Paſtours, Teachers</hi> given and ſet in the <hi>Church,</hi> for the work of the Miniſtry? And why do you ſet up a miniſtry amongſt your ſelves? <hi>Is it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:55411:40"/> you are not under the new Covenant?</hi> If God by his Immediat power and Spirit within, be the tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, why do you appoint your Miniſters before hand to ſpeak in ſuch a place, at ſuch a time? And how know you, Such a one ſhall be Immediately moved then, and not another inſtead of him? And when you invite others to your ſilent meetings, telling us, they will be ſuch, How are you aſſured that thoſe you invite may not be moved to ſpeak in that meeting? In a word, wherefore do you meet at all? will not the power move you, unleſſe you be at ſuch a meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing? None of theſe things will agree with your poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, therefore one of your friends, was (in this) ſo far ingenuous as to acknowledg that your meetings were only, and principally to encourage <hi>(that is, to Decoy, Trappan, and Inveagle)</hi> others. But before leave this queſtion, give me leave to ask you, Who, or What it is that is taught?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I am a witneſs of the moſt high God, a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the word of life, commanded by the eternal Spirit into this work,</hi> for the ſeeds ſake, <hi>which is not of the world, And to the gathering</hi> of it <hi>into the fold of ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting peace.</hi> Edw. Burroughs works p. 106.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Is nothing elſe taught, and to be taught, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this ſeed?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>To the mind which is carnal, which rules in you, the commands of Chriſt are not given, nor can be receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> Burroughs ibid. 106. <hi>The great work of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry is to point hearers to this (that is the ſeed) in them,</hi> G. Keith. Im. R. p. 77. 78.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>What muſt we underſtand by this Seed?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>That of God in thee, and in every man, the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God in thy Conſcience</hi> 'tis that we ſpeak un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:55411:40"/>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Is not this ſeed witneſs, or meaſure, Chriſt the light in man?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is ſo; The Apoſtles preached Chriſt crucifyed every where, and pointed them to him, Crucifyed in them,</hi> Keith ibid. 75, 76.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Is the command of God onely given to, and obeyed by this Seed?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Spirit, both as a rule manifeſts the promiſe, exerciſeth faith in, and fulfills the promiſes.</hi> G. White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, Chriſt aſcend. p. 10.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Is the Spirit of promiſe both the Rule, and the Subject?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I have told thee, To the mind which is carnal the commands of Chriſt are not given; And that the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, not only as a Rule manifeſts the promiſes, but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſeth faith.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <p>Then your Miniſtry is onely <hi>God preaching to himſelf, giving rules to himſelf, and obeyed onely by himſelf.</hi> Will you prate of your Infallibility, and yet talk like mad-men? Had you not loſt your common reaſon, and were abſolutely infatuated, you would not dictate after this manner: is it not high time for you to renounce theſe follies that are ſo apparently mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt? or will you chooſe <hi>(rather than to take ſhame to your ſelves)</hi> to perſiſt in your errors to your utter un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing? Be adviſed, before it be too late: think not, that becauſe you are under the bewitching influence of your own ſelf-flattery, that therefore all is well: you muſt paſſe under another Judgment than your own: though you will wickedly take upon you <hi>to adjudg others to their eternal ſtate,</hi> yet you will find, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther them, nor your ſelves, ſhall be determined by your judgments.</p>
               <p>If any of you are offended with me, for oppoſing the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> to the <hi>Quaker;</hi> let them know, I cannot,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:55411:41"/> I dare not, write contrary to my own light and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: I do not believe <hi>a true Quaker</hi> (ſuch as theſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore quoted) <hi>is a Chriſtian;</hi> but on the contrary, do look upon them as the moſt implacable enemies to the Chriſtian religion, that theſe days have brought forth. How can I think otherwiſe, ſince you deny <hi>the Perſon of Chriſt,</hi> And all your talk of redemption by him, iſſues only in this; <hi>He redeems himſelf.</hi> Your <hi>Idle non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſical, and blaſphemous prating,</hi> of God teaching the ſeed, that is to ſay, <hi>himſelf in man,</hi> renders you to me, to be men <hi>Inſpired by Satan.</hi> That you do but mock and delude men, when you talk of the <hi>Covenant of grace,</hi> is evident; for you underſtand it not, But o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly maintain <hi>a Covenant of works. For you affirm that God accepts not any who do not fulfill the law, and anſwer every demand of Juſtice.</hi> And render all that <hi>Jeſus Chriſt did for us, without us, no more but a meer example;</hi> If we ask you concerning your opinions; Preſently we are call'd <hi>Reprobates</hi> and judg'd to be in the <hi>ſorcery and witchcraft;</hi> let us urge you to be plain, you put us off with <hi>your witneſſings;</hi> if in one place you ſeem to own the truth, in another, you will in down-right terms deny it: <hi>let this be ſignified to you,</hi> Then Immediately you curſe us, ſo that no man knows when, nor how to believe you, If we ſpeak <hi>you,</hi> to a ſingle perſon, you reprove us for not uſing the <hi>pure language.</hi> If we ſay <hi>thou</hi> to an Individua<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Quaker;</hi> you will upbraid us with <hi>Jeering or hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie:</hi> you bid us follow the light within us; And if we do ſo, you will load us, with moſt bitter revilings, you will Appropriate to your ſelves the priviledge of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibility, and at as if you were unaccountable either to God, or man, for what you ſay, or do. Though <hi>your ſentiments,</hi> neither agree with <hi>the Scriptures, you<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="69" facs="tcp:55411:41"/> ſelves,</hi> nor <hi>the common reaſon of mankind;</hi> yet will you Impoſe upon us, and <hi>that under the ſevereſt cenſures,</hi> the belief of your unknown, and <hi>unintelligible doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines.</hi> You are as <hi>vile Impoſtors</hi> as ever were; for you will inſinuate your <hi>lying doctrines,</hi> with <hi>lyes,</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade many credulous, and ignorant (yet welmean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) people, that you indeed believe, <hi>what in truth you do not:</hi> And accuſe your Adverſaries of that, <hi>where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they are innocent:</hi> your manner is not, to convince us of error, <hi>but to conclude us ſo, right or wrong.</hi> If any miſcarriage be, that muſt be improved to make the truth it ſelf odious: neither do you only undermine religion, but <hi>your principles Improved</hi> are deſtructive to all humane ſociety: you tell us, <hi>'tis witchcraft to take up a command from the Scriptures,</hi> And <hi>that is no command to me, which is a command to another.</hi> If then a <hi>father</hi> command his child, The <hi>child</hi> may reply <hi>Thou muſt wait for my obedience till I be moved.</hi> The like may every ſubject and ſervant plead. If a <hi>mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant fell you his goods,</hi> He muſt ſtay for his money, <hi>till you be moved to pay it,</hi> til which time, you are under <hi>no obligation in point of duty:</hi> you ſay 'tis neceſſary to have things reveal'd to you <hi>with reſpect to your converſation in the world,</hi> which are not to be found in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, no not by conſequence; How then may your creditors be aſſured, it will be reveal'd to you, to pay what you owe them. <hi>Scripture, and reaſon would, and do, teach you herein,</hi> but theſe you muſt be dead unto; who knows then what may, or may not be reveal'd to you? 'Tis not unknown, that <hi>a Revelation hath been pretended, to excuſe the payment of a juſt debt.</hi> And why may not that which hath been <hi>(even a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you)</hi> be again? But is it reaſonable that men ſhould be baffled out of their juſt rights, <hi>by ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:55411:42"/> and wicked pretences,</hi> go on, yet aſſuredly know that God will bring you to judgment. Then you ſhall know (though now you will not) by whom ſuch do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines as theſe <hi>(that are and have been the peſt, and plague of the world, and the ſcandal and reproach of religion,)</hi> were Inſpired. Theſe things being conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, whether you be not either diſtracted or worſe, I ſhall leave with others to think on; in the mean while, I judg my ſelf ſufficiently warranted in oppoſing the Chriſtian to the Quaker.</p>
            </sp>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. H.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:55411:42"/>
            <head>The Subſtance of the <hi>Quakers</hi> Belief in the Points before diſcourſed, compriz'd in this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing Catechiſm, for the more eaſie remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of ſuch, who are of weaker capacities.</head>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>WHat is your opinion of the Scriptures?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> That they are neither a rule to us, nor a means to know God, nor how to worſhip him. <hi>G. Whitehead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thou mayſt burn thy Bible, and ſerve God as well without. <hi>N. Lucas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Is there any thing more made known to you, than what is revealed in the Scriptures?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> There is a neceſſity for thoſe under the new Covenant, to have things reveal'd to them which are not to be found in the Scriptures particularly, not ſo much as by conſequence. <hi>G. Keith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Are we not to obey the commands in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> They who take up a command from the letter, and ſay Chriſt commands it, are in the witchcraft. <hi>Ed. Burroughs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>May we not pray for thoſe mercies we want, and give thanks for mercies received, except we have an Immediate motion, and Impulſe to do it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 'Tis an error to ſay, We are not to wait for an inward call, motion, Impulſe or Inſpiration; to pray or give thanks, ſo, as to forbear till it be given. <hi>Geo. Keith.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="72" facs="tcp:55411:43"/>
            <p>Q. <hi>If I never be moved to pray,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>am I not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Is it of good report for un-inſpired men to pray? <hi>W. Pen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Will you ſay, tis of evil report if they doe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> What thou doſt without an inward motion is accurſed. <hi>Edw. Burroughs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All thoſe duties that have ſin in them, had better be let alone.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>If the want of an Inward and Immediate motion will excuſe us from duty, what ſignifies the Law, which God hath given to man to oblige him thereunto?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> That is no command, <hi>(or Law)</hi> to me, which is given to another man, <hi>Edw. Burrows.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Are not all men ſinleſs, except, when they obey not an inward motion?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> I have told thee, that they who take up a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand from the letter are in the witchcraft. <hi>Ed. Bur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>God rules the Stars by his Immediate power, they being not capable of being govern'd by any other rule; and if God do only govern, and rule man by immediate motions, wherein doth a Man differ from a Star?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Now thou runs into the imaginations.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Either God hath given a rule to man or not, and this rule is known, or 'tis not? If there be a known rule, then either it obligeth at all times, or but at ſome; if the former, man alwayes ſins if he obeys not; if the latter, aſſign thoſe times when he is under no rule.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. I think not meet to ſatisfie thy buſie mind.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>If inward motions, impulſes, or inſpirations be the onely rule, to every Individual; why do you ſet up a court amongſt your ſelves, to give rules to others?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. We being a religious Body have a power with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in our ſelves, <hi>W. Pen Sp. Alex. p.</hi> 6.</p>
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:55411:43"/>
            <p>Q. <hi>By what rule ſhall I be aſſured of that?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. We as a believing body, have the holy Spirit, we know we are of God, and the world that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand our teſtimony are in the Gall of bitterneſs, and in the bond of iniquity, <hi>W. P. ibid.</hi> 13.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Is not this to juſtifie what is ſaid of you? they that will not believe your ſayings, you will not ſpare to cenſure them: but do not you herein apparently ſet up the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Body above the Light within?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. We deny that to be Light which oppoſeth the the Judgment of the body <hi>W. P. ibid.</hi> 14. The body will have a true ſenſe, feeling and underſtanding, of motions, viſions, revelations, and doctrines; therfore 'tis ſafeſt to make her the touchſtone in all things relating to God, <hi>Sp. of the Hat, p.</hi> 21.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What ſafty can there be in relying on ſuch a body, that act by no known rule or law?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. We have the power: And will not ſuch that are in the power do right? <hi>ibid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>By what known rule, do you exert your power, that ſo the peccant perſon may be convinced you do him no wrong?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. We, as a Body, have power to determine, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we abhor, renounce, rebuke, with all ſeverity, that rude imagination of the Hat on in publick Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. <hi>W. Pen Sp. of Alex. p.</hi> 4, 5. 9.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>You take that for graunted which is denied, how do you make it appear you have ſuch a power?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Thou art angry, not that there is a rule, but that thou haſt no ſhare in it, <hi>W. Pen. Sp. of Alex. p.</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Is not this as much as to ſay, that the will and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the Elders is the rule, and not the light within: if ſo, what ſignifies all your conteſts, about the ſufficiency of the light in every man?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="74" facs="tcp:55411:44"/>
            <p>A. I have told thee that we know we are of God, and they who withſtand our Teſtimony are in the gall of bitterneſs, <hi>W. Pen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>If your pretences be ſufficient to determine other perſons, why may not the like pretence in them determine you? If you urge the Scriptures or primitive practice for your rule, you will entangle your ſelves. If you ſay, The body (or court) is the rule; then, you ſet up the Body both above the Scriptures, and the light within. Will not a little meaſure of light diſcover your folly herein?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I ſhall proceed to another queſtion: Who or what is Jeſus Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. 'Tis God himſelf <hi>W. Pen.</hi> 'Tis the light in us <hi>Nayler and Hubberthorn.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>It is ſaid that Jeſus Chriſt was crucifyed: but is it ſafe to ſay, God himſelf or the Light within was cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Yee have condemned, and kill'd the juſt, that is, Chriſt Jeſus in their hearts; him they crucifyed in his appearance, <hi>G. Keith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Is Chriſt one thing, and his Appearance ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Yea For Chriſt as he is and lives, in himſelf cannot be crucifyed, but his appearance may, <hi>G. Keith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>When the Scriptures ſpeak of Chriſt crucifyed, do they mean onely his Appearance, and not Himſelf? and is this meaning ſolid?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Yea.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why do you ſpeak, and write ſo darkly and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully of the perſon of Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. You are not able to bear what we have to hold forth concerning Him: ſhould we deliver what we hold concerning Jeſus Chriſt, we ſhould be ſtoned in
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:55411:44"/> the ſtreets, <hi>Rob. Waſtfield.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What think you of that-Chriſt, who was born at</hi> Bethlem, <hi>and dyed at</hi> Jeruſalem?</p>
            <p>A. Jeſus Chriſt at <hi>Jeruſalem, a type, figure, a ſhad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, that is paſt away.</hi> Do you, when you riſe in the morning, think on God; do you ſee God in every creature and in your ſelf: think on theſe things <hi>and trouble not your ſelf about Jeſus at</hi> Jeruſalem. <hi>[This was uttered before many credible witneſſes, by an emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Quaker.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Is not Jeſus Chriſt a diſtinct perſon without you?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Jeſus Chriſt a perſon without us, is not Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-language, but the <hi>Anthropomorphits,</hi> and <hi>Mug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gletonians: G. Whitehead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Is not Chriſt in perſon at Gods right hand?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Jeſus Chriſt is at Gods right hand, but I cannot believe he hath a perſonal Being at the right hand of God, <hi>G. W.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What do you intend by Gods right hand?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Chriſt, nor Gods right hand, is not to be limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to a remoteneſs from the Saints, <hi>G.W.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What is the meaning of that text, The ſame Jeſus that went away, ſhall in like manner come again,</hi> Acts 1.10, 11.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> I deny he ſhall come viſibly, and though it be ſaid [in like manner,] yet every like is not the ſame, <hi>G. Whitehead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Do not you believe that Chriſt will come the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time without ſin to Salvation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> He is come the ſecond time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. 'Tis true: Chriſt is come by his Spirit but is there not another Coming?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> What other Coming wouldſt thou have?</p>
            <pb n="76" facs="tcp:55411:45"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. The Scriptures ſpeak of his Coming to judg both the quick and the dead: do you beleive this?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Why doſt thou trouble thy ſelf about ſuch fooliſh and ſilly things;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Pray, anſwer directly, whether you believe Chriſt ſhall come to judge the quick and the dead?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> I perceive that which troubles thee is the puz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling thy ſelf ſo much in that book <hi>(the Bible)</hi> thou wilt never be ſettled till thou throw away that Book.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Do you deny the ſecond perſonal Coming of Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> They are like to be deceived who are expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that Chriſts ſecond Coming will be perſonal <hi>G. Whitehead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What ſignifies thoſe words, When he comes every eye ſhall ſee him, they that peirced him</hi> &amp;c?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To ſay, they, that peirced that body, ſhall ſee that body, are not Scripture-words. <hi>G. Whitehead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Hath Chriſt no body?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yea, the Church is his body, <hi>Ed. Burroughs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Hath Chriſt no other body but his Church?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> This is an enſnaring queſtion, <hi>Ed. Bur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What ſnare can be in it, if you beleive he hath another Body?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To ſay, Chriſt hath two bod<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es, one out of the ſight of the Saints, there is ſo much wickedneſs, and ignorance in the broachers hereof, that it needs no anſwer, <hi>Edw. Burroughs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Is not this as much as to ſay, Chriſt hath no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Body but his Church?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> They that accuſe us for ſaying, Chriſt hath but one body, ſhould produce plain Scripture that ſaith, he hath two, <hi>G. W.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Is there no other Chriſt but the Light within?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="77" facs="tcp:55411:45"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> I have already ſaid that they who deny Chriſt to be the light in every man, are Antichriſts, <hi>Ed. Bur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What doth the word Chriſt ſignifie?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Anointed;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. If the light be Chriſt, what is its <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction? and to what end is it anointed? and how may we conceive it capable to execute the office of a Prieſt, Prophet, and King?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Now thou runs into thy fleſhly Conceivings;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Is Chriſt in you, in reſpect of that nature in which he ſuffered at</hi> Jeruſalem?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Here thou Enemy of Chriſt wouldſt know how the Saints injoy Chriſt. Thou art in the nature that <hi>Judas</hi> was in, who betrayed him, <hi>Ed. Burroughs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Doth Chriſt, really in theſe days, take upon him, the form of a Servant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Thou dark beaſt, and conjurer, querying with thy conjured words: Is Chriſt to be limitted to days, in taking upon him the form of a ſervant? <hi>Ed. Bur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Is this anſwer ſerious and to the queſtion?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yea, bleſſed be the Lord; 'tis an anſwer in the eternal life and light. <hi>Ed. Burroughs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Is it not Impious, to intitle God to ſuch railing and impertinent Anſwers?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Thou ſhalt eternally witneſs them. <hi>Ed. Bur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Was Jeſus Chriſt the gift of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> He was ſo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Wherein doth that appear?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> His doctrine, life, miracles, death and ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings to God, is the gift and expreſſion of God's eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal love for the ſalvation of men. <hi>W. Pen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Thou haſt affirmed, that God is Chriſt, did then God himſelf dye, and ſuffer to God? &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Wilt thou deny that Chriſt is God's gift?</p>
            <pb n="78" facs="tcp:55411:46"/>
            <p>Q. <hi>Wilt thou prove that God gave himſelf to dye and ſuffer to God, therein to expreſs his eternal love for the ſalvation of men?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> This a captious and enſnaring queſtion.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>I perceive thou art entangled, and it will be to little purpoſe to preſs thee to reconcile one dictate with another: however, pray ſhew, wherein Chriſt was given for the ſalvation of men?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. 1. In aboliſhing the other Covenant which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted of ſhaddowy Ordinances.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In promulgating his meſſage of a moſt free, and univerſal tender of Life to all that believe, and follow him the Light, in all his righteouſneſs.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In ſeconding his Doctrine with ſigns and mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, and a moſt innocent and a holy life.</p>
            <p n="4">4. In ratifying and confirming all with great love, and a holy reſignation, by offering up his body to be crucified by wicked hands; and is thereby become a moſt compleat Captain and perfect Example. <hi>W. Pen, Sad. Found.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Of what were thoſe Ordinances ſhaddows?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Of the Light and Life.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Was not the light and life, at that time in the Jews?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Yea, but not in that meaſure and degree, as af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards ſhould be.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Were they then ſhaddows onely of ſuch a meaſure or degree as in future times ſhould be vouchſafed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Figures and ſhaddows are onely in force till the ſubſtance comes. <hi>W. Pen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Is not the light and life the ſubſtance?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. The light, is the ſame Jeſus, in his firſt appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, as the ſeed of light, not come forth to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect day. <hi>G. Keith.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="79" facs="tcp:55411:46"/>
            <p>Q. <hi>If then Jeſus Chriſt in his firſt Appearance was at that time in the Jews, then thoſe ordinances could not be ſhaddows of that: Of what then were they ſo?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. As Chriſt apprehending the weakneſs of his diſciples, did think fit to leave them ſome figurative token, and mark of his remembrance for them to be in the practice of, till he was better known to them, myſtically, and in the ſpirit, therefore he ſaid, Do this till I come. <hi>W. Pen. Apol.</hi> 134.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>But were the Jewiſh ordinances figures only of Chriſt myſtically, and in the Spirit?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. They were ſo;</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Was not Chriſt known myſtically and in the Spirit, at that time?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Not as afterwards he would be;</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>If they were ſhaddows of ſomething farther to be reveal'd, Whether that degree of light they then had, was not inſufficient?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. There is a ſufficiency in the leaſt degree of light, to help, and ſave him that takes heed to it. <hi>S. Fiſher.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Is not that which is able to ſave, the ſubſtance?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. It is ſo;</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Are types, figures, ſhaddows, of force and to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved when the ſubſtance is come?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. When the ſubſtance is come, the ſhaddow ceaſeth in point of Inſtitution. <hi>W. Pen. Apol,</hi> 134.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Were not thoſe ſhaddows Inſtituted by God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A They were ſo.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Were the Jews obliged to obſerve them?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Yea,</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Then Either the ſubſtance was not come, or they were no ſhaddows, or elſe they were ordain'd for ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther end, and purpoſe: thus are you in a maze, and run your ſelves into Irreconcilable abſurdities, and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:55411:47"/> pray, what was that doctrine which Chriſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conded by Miracles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. That all men ſhould take heed to him, the Light of them.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Foraſmuch as all men acknowledge a light to be in every man, and that it ought to be heeded, what need was there of miracles to confirme this?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. But all men do not acknowledg the light in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man, to be the Chriſt of God.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Very true, were the Miracles then to prove this?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Yea.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Where was ſuch a doctrine delivered by Chriſt, and ſeconded by Miracles?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Doth not Chriſt ſay, He is the light of men.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Where doth he ſay, The light in every man is the Chriſt of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. They who deny the light in every man to be the Chriſt, are Antichriſts. <hi>Ed. Bur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What farther did Chriſt deliver as his doctrine, which he ſeconded by Miracles?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. A meſſage of a moſt free, univerſal tender of life to all that believe, and follow him the light in all his righteouſneſs. <hi>W. Pen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Was this all he ſeconded by miracles?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Yea.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Doſt thou do well to ſay ſo, ſince the Scriptures teach us otherwiſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. What other Doctrine did he confirm by mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles?</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Was it not this, That he himſelf was the Meſſiah promiſed, and was ſent into the world to dye for ſinners? and is not this that doctrine you ſo Strenuouſly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugn?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:55411:47"/>
            <p>A. Now thou inſinuates a ſlander againſt us.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What further did Chriſt do for the Salvation of men?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. He did ratifie and confirm all with great love, and a holy reſignation by offering up his body to be crucified by wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed hands, and thereby became a moſt compleat captain, and perfect example. <hi>W. Pen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Was Chriſt in his ſufferings no more but an Example?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. What more, wouldſt have him to be?</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Was not the love of God, herein manifeſt, in ſending his Son to dye for ſinners?</hi> Rom. 5.8.</p>
            <p>A. There may be ſomething of that in it.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How, and in what reſpect did Chriſt dye for ſinners?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Not to make ſatisfaction for their ſins: the conſequence of ſuch a doctrine is both Irreligious, and Irrational <hi>W. Pen. Sandy Found. p.</hi> 16.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What doth the Scripture mean in ſaying, He was made ſin for us?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. I caution and warn men, by no means to entertain this principle <hi>(viz.)</hi> of Chriſts Satisfaction by whomſoever re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended. O why ſhould this Horrible thing be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for by Chriſtians? <hi>W. Pen. ibid. p.</hi> 16. 25. 30.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How was ſin, laid on Chriſt, and how was he made a curſe for us?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. God was ſatisfied in his Son Chriſt the anointed, the Lamb offer'd without ſpot a ſacrifice for Sin. <hi>G. W. Div. of Chriſt. p.</hi> 19.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>In what reſpect was Chriſt a ſacrifice for Sin?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Your abuſe of Chriſt, confuſion, and darkneſs in ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting your matter we cannot own, as proceeding from any ſenſe or ſavour of Chriſt either as Sacrifice, or a Saviour, <hi>G. W. ibid.</hi> 79. 80.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Was that body of Jeſus which was offer'd upon the croſs the one, and onely, Sacrifice for Sin?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Thy ſottiſh queries riſeth out of thy dark mind con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the body of Jeſus, as the Devill did about the body
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:55411:48"/> of <hi>Moſes, Edward Burroughs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Was Chriſts death a ſatisfactory Sacrifice, or not?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> God ſatisfyed himſelf in his own gift, and without performing his own will he could not be ſatisfyed, <hi>G. W. ibid.</hi> 79.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. If thou hadſt ſaid, that God made man and gave him a reaſonable Soul,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and without performing his own will he could not be ſatisfyed, would it not have been, as much to the queſtion, as what thou haſt ſaid: anſwer me, Was Chriſts death on the Croſs ſatisfactory for the ſins of the world? or only for the Elect?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Thou Jeſuit art pleading for a Chriſt a far off, that Chriſt did not ſatisfie for thee, thou art under the woe. The death of Chriſt we witneſs, <hi>Edw. Bur.</hi> Where reads thou that God requires ſatisfaction for the ſins of the Elect, or laid any thing to their charge, thou blind ignorant Sot? <hi>Edward Burroughs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What was Chriſts end, in giving himſelf a ranſome, in being a propitiation for the ſins of the whole world?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To ſhew forth, and give teſtimony of Gods love, and grace towards all mankind, G. W.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. VVherein was that Love and Grace manifeſted in Chriſt being a ſacrifice for all men?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> He gave Him a ranſome, to redeem, and purchaſe man out of the Tranſgreſſion, G. W.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. VVas it the will of God that Chriſt ſhould dye to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem man out of the Tranſgreſſion?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It was ſo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. VVas there a neceſſity hereof?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> God would not be ſatisfied without performing his own will, G. W.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. If it was Gods will, to give his Son to be a propitiation for the ſins of the whole world; And if there was a neceſſity that thus it ſhould be, becauſe (as you ſay) God cannot be ſatisfyed without doing his own will, How then can the meer
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:55411:48"/> Light within be ſufficient to ſave? if it were, what neceſſity could there be of Chriſt being a ſacrifice? but if this were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, then why do you maintain the former?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Now thou multiplies queſtions to enſnare.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Pray be ſerious, and acquaint me what that obedience or ſuffering is by which you are reconciled to God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Silence, fleſh! Would thou who art an Enemy of God know how the Saints are reconciled to God? <hi>Edw. Bur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. VVill you not inform me in this matter?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Own the Light in thy conſcience, and then thou ſhalt know. <hi>Edwards Burroughs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. VVhat think you of Juſtification by that Righteouſneſs which Chriſt in his own perſon fulfilled for us, wholly without us?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> I boldly affirm it to be a Doctrine of Devills. W. Pen.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Is there no other Righteouſneſs by which and for the ſake of which the Saints are juſtified, than what Chriſt works in them?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Thou art accurſed, thou Beaſt, upon whom the wrath of God muſt be accompliſhed, who would have another Righteouſneſs, than what Chriſt works in the Saints, <hi>Edw. Burroughs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Is there no ſuch thing as an imputed righteouſneſs?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Juſtification is not from the imputation of anothers righteouſneſs, <hi>W. Pen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Doth God juſtifie men upon the account of their own works?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Was not <hi>Abraham</hi> juſtifyed by works? and was not his perſonal offering up of <hi>Iſaac</hi> the ground of that juſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation? <hi>W. Pen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Are good works meritorious?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> They may be ſaid to procure, deſerve, or obtain, <hi>W. Pen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Doth then the holy lives, and works, of the Saints juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie them in the ſight of God, from the guilt of ſin?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="84" facs="tcp:55411:49"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Thou dead beaſt, by the ſame that the Saints are juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, thou art condemn'd into the lake for ever, <hi>Edw. Bur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Are none juſtified or Righteous in the ſight of God in whom is any corruption or failing?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Thou polluted Beaſt, God accepts not any, where there is any failing, or who do not fulfill the law, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer every demand of juſtice, <hi>Edw. Burroughs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Who, what, is the true miniſtry?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> God himſelf by his immediate power, Spirit, and unction within, is the teacher of his people, <hi>G. Whitehead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Who, or what doth he teach?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The Seed;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Is the ſeed the onely object of this teaching?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To the mind which is carnal the commands of God are not given, nor can they be received, <hi>Edw. Bur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What is this ſeed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 'Tis that of God in thee, the witneſs of God in thy conſcience;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Do not you ſometimes call this ſeed Chriſt, and his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> We do.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Is the command given only to, and obeyed by this Seed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The Spirit both as a rul manifeſts the promiſes, and exerciſeth Faith, <hi>G. W.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Is not this as much us to ſay, that God preacheth to, and is obeyed only by himſelf? Are you not aſhamed to prate thus?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Is not the great work of the miniſtry to point to this (<hi>viz.</hi> the Seed) in them, <hi>G. K?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Is it credible that God ſhould teach only himſelf?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Thy dark mind cannot conceive theſe things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Doſt thou thy ſelf underſtand them?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yea.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. VVhy wilt thou not endeavour to inform me?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> What haſt thou to do to talk of theſe things, thot knoweſt nothing of God and Chriſt.</p>
            <pb n="85" facs="tcp:55411:49"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Do you not ſay, I have a light in me?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> I do.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. VVhat is this Light?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Thou art an Idle fellow, <hi>thus one of their Miniſters anſwered this queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Muſt I obey this Light?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yea.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. If I do obey it, will it certainly ſave me?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> There is no doubt of that;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. VVhat aſſurance may I have thereof?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> If it do not, I dare be hang<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, R. W.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Of what advantage will thy hanging be to me, if I ſhould miſcarry!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Now thou taunts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Doſt thou not adminiſter the occaſion?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> I ſee thou art ſtill in the envious mind.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Do you believe a ſtate of Immmortality and eternal feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> We own, and witneſs to an Immortal ſtate, Geo. W.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Do you believe a farther happineſs ſhall be injoy'd by the Saints, at the laſt day, than now?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> When thinks thou that will bee? muſt all the Saints have their hopes, and faith of Salvation, unanſwered till then? G. W. <hi>Chr. Aſc. p.</hi> 34.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Do not you wait for any thing farther?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Surely, death, and darkneſs hath power over thy mind, elſe thou would'ſt never ſhew thy ſelf ſuch an igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Papiſt, in putting Salvation ſo far off, till thou know'ſt not when, according to thy carnal conceits, G. W. <hi>ibid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Is eternal life, and felicity injoy'd now?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Is not the recompence of reward, Eternal life, and felicity, inwardly, and Spiritually received, by thoſe that <hi>Now</hi> ſuffer for Chriſt, G. W. ibid. p. 37.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Is your belief in theſe points conſonant to the Doctrine delivered in the holy Scripture?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="86" facs="tcp:55411:50"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> I have told thee that it is neceſſary for us to have things, reveal'd to us that are not to be found in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, particularly not ſo much as by conſequence, <hi>G. Keith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Muſt we be concluded meerly by your ſayings and Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> We are of God, and they who withſtand our teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony are in the gall of bitterneſs. W. Pen. Such that inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogate us, we will tell them, they are Reprobates, and in the Sorcery and Witchcraft, Enemies to the life, that they are filthy polluted Beaſts; Serpents, querying with conjured words, and that they are blind, and ignorant Sots, <hi>Edw. Bur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Is what you ſay concerning ſuch, certainly true?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The Judgment we paſſe upon them, they ſhall eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally Witneſs, <hi>Edw. Burroughs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. If ſuch as</hi> Edw. Burroughs, George Whitehead, <hi>and</hi> W. Pen. <hi>may be accounted true Miniſters, whom ſhall we e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem falſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> They who ſay the Scriptures are the rule, that deny Chriſt to be the Light in every man.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Doth not your Miniſtry, deny Chriſts Perſon, main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain juſtification by works, and that not according to the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the ſecond, but of the firſt covenant? curſing people for doing what they bid them; Impoſe on us the groſſeſt falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoods, and moſt irreconcileable contradictions, under the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of immediate Inſpirations, as if it were not enough for them to be wicked alone, unleſſe they could make God himſelf (O Horrid villany!) an acceſſory with them? A ſort of men, that will affirm, and deny at pleaſure: One while ſay, they own the Perſon of Chriſt; Another while, deny he hath any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal being without men: Now they will confeſſe the very Chriſt who dyed at <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> anon they tell us, that Chriſt was but a figure, a ſhaddow paſſed away, and why ſhould we trouble our ſelves with that Jeſus, and, To concern our ſelves about his ſecond perſonal Coming is but puzling about ſilly and fooliſh things. When they ſay Chriſt came to redeem man; If
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:55411:50"/> we ſift their meaning, 'tis nothing but the Seed, the principle of God in man that wants redemption.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>If we tell them of their faults they aggravate them, by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting therein, and whil'ſt they rail at their accuſers, juſtifie the Accuſation it ſelf, as is the manner of your Dictator:</hi> Will. Pen. <hi>who of late hath been ſo extravagant in his wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, that ſcarce a man that reads him but thinks him to be either diſtracted or worſe, and yet muſt we believe ſuch as theſe are true Miniſters?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Why ſpeakeſt thou ſo ſeverely againſt W. Pen?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Have I not ſufficient reaſon?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I profeſs, were I, as he, I would ſue thee at the Common-Law, <hi>thus an eminent Quaker ſpoke to a friend of mine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. VVhy ſo?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe thou haſt diſparaged him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Hath</hi> W. Pen <hi>a diſpenſation to write or ſpeak without controul, Is he a <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Dictator?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. I would have him ſeek his remedy againſt thee at the Common-Law;</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVould ſuch a practice, agree with your principle of Liberty of Conſcience?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Liberty to reflect on ſuch as W. Pen, is not to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd: no Liberty but in the Power, <hi>G. Fox.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. You take a Liberty to curſe, and revile others, who give you no juſt cauſe. And may not we take notice when, or wherein you err, and ſoberly put you in mind thereof?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. What we do is nothing to thee, we are in the Power; we know we are of God, therefore all that withſtand our teſtimony are in the gall of bitterneſs, W. Pen.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. If now under your preſent circumſtances, you manifeſt ſuch a mind; what might we expect from you, were your Power anſwerable to your VVills?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Alas for thee! we are an innocent people.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. VVe have nothing but your own words for it; your en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venom'd malice againſt others, your Tyrannical actings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:55411:51"/> your ſelves, gives us ſufficient intimations, that 'twill be dangerous truſting the Old man in you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A farther account of you, and your Tenets, you may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect as opportunity and occaſion is offered: as yet I have moſtly been concerned about your opinions, and have been ſparing touching your practices, which is not for want of Inſtances, for I do give you to underſtand, That as Horrid enormities are raigning under the vizor and garb of a Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, as amongſt any other ſort of men; only with this diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, Yours are more Aggravated, by your pretences to perfection, which pretence is no more than a meer fraud, whereby you deceive many ſimple people. If therefore you will provoke me to ſpeak all I can, either reſpecting your opinions, or practices, blame not me, but thank your ſelves if the event anſwer not your expectation.</p>
            <trailer>The End.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>PAg. 13. lin. 16. for ſalvation, r. ſalutation, p. 26. l. 6. dele Chriſt, l. 7. r. Chriſt, p. 68. l. 32. for at r. act, p. 79. l. 18. for ſufficient, r. in ſufficient.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
